<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The earnest breathings of forreign Protestants, divines &amp; others, to the ministers and other able Christians of these three nations for a compleat body of practicall divinity ... and an essay of a modell of the said body of divinity / by J.D. ... ; together with an expedient tendered for the entertainment of strangers who are Protestants, and by their means to advance the Gospel unto their several nations and quarters ...</title>
            <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 232 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37065</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2855</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3545</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12784060</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12784060</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93868</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37065)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93868)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 379:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The earnest breathings of forreign Protestants, divines &amp; others, to the ministers and other able Christians of these three nations for a compleat body of practicall divinity ... and an essay of a modell of the said body of divinity / by J.D. ... ; together with an expedient tendered for the entertainment of strangers who are Protestants, and by their means to advance the Gospel unto their several nations and quarters ...</title>
                  <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 57 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. Underhill ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: John Dury.</note>
                  <note>Errata on p. 57.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestant churches --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93868:1"/>
            <p>THE EARNEST BREATHINGS OF Forreign Proteſtants, DIVINES &amp; Others: TO THE Miniſters and other able Chriſtians of theſe three NATIONS, FOR A COMPLEAT BODY OF Practicall Divinity,</p>
            <p>And CASES, wherein the Grace of God hath more Eminently appeared amongſt us in theſe Iſlands, then in the reſt of the World beſides.</p>
            <p>Which Work hath been long in the Heads and Hearts of many Worthy Men to be undertaken, as appeareth by a Letter written to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> who much approved the ſame.</p>
            <p>And an Eſſay of a Modell of the ſaid <hi>Body of Divinity,</hi> by <hi>J. D.</hi> Highly approved by D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>George Horne,</hi> Profeſſor of the Univerſity of LEYDEN.</p>
            <p>Together with an Expedient tendered for the entertainment of Strangers, who are Proteſtants, and by their means to advance the Goſpel unto their ſeveral Nations and Quarters.</p>
            <p>Humbly tendered to his Highneſs, the next Parliament, and the good People of the Land.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Underhill,</hi> at the Anchor in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93868:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93868:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the GODLY &amp; LEARNED Profeſſors and Heads of Colledges In the two Famous UNIVERSITIES OF THE Common-wealth of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore ever this Requeſt was made by Forrain Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants to our Worthies in</hi> England, <hi>and when I was at the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of</hi> Cambridge <hi>many years ago, the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of ſuch a Work as is here implored, was made apparent unto me, and my wiſhes and earneſt endeavours were made awake towards it; but then there was no ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance that ever any ſuch thing could, or ſhould be brought to paſſe: yet ſince we have ſeen greater and more unexpected mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters accompliſhed, both in reference to Religion, and to the Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I hope we are in a fair way to ſee yet greater things brought forth, and things of Peace and Comfort to all the Churches, which may prove to be the foundations of many Generations. For as the hope of the Hypocrite ſhall periſh, and be like unto the giving up of the ghost; ſo the deſire of the Righteouſ ſhall be fulfilled, and he ſhall not be aſhamed of his hopes, becauſe the Promiſe is, that</hi> he who hungers and thirſts for Righteouſneſſe, ſhall be ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now the Work which is here ſued for by the Forrain Miniſters, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but the knowledge of that way of Righteouſneſſe which God hath prepared for his Saints to walk in, that they may have Communion with him in his Kingdom. Therefore I am very confident that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will be ſo fully revealed and made known, that</hi> a man <hi>(as the Prophet ſaith)</hi> though a fool ſhall not erre therein. <hi>And becauſe the Lord hath given unto you</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:93868:3"/> vour the accompliſhment of their requeſt; I think my ſelf bound in Conſcience at this ſeaſonable time, to offer it to your pious thoughts, in the expreſſe words of their own Petition, and in ſome Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which I have annexed unto the matter thereof.</p>
            <p>Therefore in the firſt place, you ſhall find here a Copy of their Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition in Latine, with the ſeveral ſubſcriptions, whereof the Original writings are in my hand, which I have put in Engliſh to ſatisfie Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Capacities: Then in the ſecond place, you will find three conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable matters concerning this ſute repreſented unto you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What is meant by a Body of Practical Divinity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What the Reaſons are, for which it ought to be publiſhed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. How the Work may be effected, and imparted unto thoſe that have ſued for it at our hands.</p>
            <p>Which having endeavoured to make you ſenſible of, as a Work moſt acceptable unto God, moſt ſutable to the Goſpel, moſt profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table unto the Godly, very uſefull unto all, very honourable unto theſe our Churches, and not difficult in it ſelf to be effected, if it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive but a little Countenance, I ſhall by the further proſecution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as God ſhall give me addreſſes and opportunities, reſt ſatisfied in this (whatever the ſucceſſe and event may be) that I have not been wanting to the diſcharge of my duty, nor to the deſires of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſo farre as God hath enabled me to proceed towards the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing of the ſame. And thus commending to the grace of God thy ſenſe of this buſineſſe, I ſhall ſubſcribe my ſelf thy Servant therein</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Dury.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:93868:3"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="lat">
               <body>
                  <head>Eccleſiarum Magnae Britanniae at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Hyberniae patronis &amp; Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtibus Primariis, Eximiis Dei ſervis, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Eccleſiae Laborantis in Germania fautoribus Colendiſſimis, ſit Gratia &amp; Pax à Deo Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, &amp; Domino noſtro Jeſu Chriſto per Spiritûs ſancti Communionem, <hi>AMEN.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Iverſa Spiritûs Dei dona membris Eccleſiae diverſis eſſe conceſſa, &amp; ſacra oracula teſtantur, &amp; res ipſa loquitur; finem tamen eundem Communis Aedificationis mutuae<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> utilitatis liquet Patri luminum, datori omnis doni perfecti, propoſitum eſſe in omnium donorum largitione. Apoſtolus enim dicit,</hi> Unicui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> datam eſſe Spiritûs declarationem <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: <hi>&amp; alib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> jubemur,</hi> Ut quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> accepit donum, ità alius in alium illud ſubminiſtrer, ut decet bonos gratiae Dei diverſae <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Talentum enim quod à Deo ſinguli accepimus, fidei noſtrae commiſſum eſt, ut illius dispenſatores facti, non illud defodiamus, ut nequam ille ſervus, in terram; ſed ad Domini emolumentum impendamus, ut cum fidelibus ejus ſervis, plura tam Domino quàm nobis ipſis lucrifacere talenta poſſimus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Haec cò spectant, Illuſtres, Clariſſimi<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Viri, Reverendiſſimi<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Reverendiin Chriſto Patres &amp; Fratres, ut cùm nobis certò innotuerit inter Eccleſias magnae Britanniae, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinam Theologiae Practicae multorum piè Doctorum Eccleſiae veſtrae Antiſtitum publicis ſcriptis egregiè excultam eſſe, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad uſum Popularem inſigniter accomodatam, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> eam ſolummodò linguae veſtrae Cancellis tanquam reconditum ab exteris Nationibus theſaurum contineri, &amp; aſſervari, maximám<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> utilitatem ad omnes Eccleſias Chriſtianas, praeſertìm autem Evangelicas redundaturam, ſi quae vobis in hoc genere peculiaria ſunt, publicentur, ità ut ab its quo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> legi &amp; intelligi poſſint, ut (inquam, cùm haec ità ſe habeant) Illuſtrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Reverentiis Veſtris votum nostrum ac deſiderium aperiamus, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> per ſanctae Communionis in Chriſto vinculum, fraternae<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> libertatis Parrheſiam rogemus, vos praeſertim quotquot inter Eccleſiarum Rectores, Protectores, &amp; Fautares estis aedificationis Publicae verè ſtudioſi, ne permittatis hoc Talentum tam pretioſum ulterijis abſcondi &amp; occultari ab Exoticorum manibus &amp; oculis, ſed velitis pro prudentia veſtra, pro ferventis erga frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas Eccleſias Charitatis, ac liberalis ſtudii erga Dei gloriam in Evangelii propagatione, pio zelo &amp; affectu veſtro rationem aliquam inire commodam, quâ Medulla Authorum in illo genere apud vos extantium &amp; eminentium ex omnibus collecta in volumen aliquod conji<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciatur, ſive Locorum Communium, ſive Syſtematis Theologiae practicae, quod publici juris ſit, &amp; omnium manibus teri poſſit linguâ notâ &amp; doctioribus communi: Audivimus pauca quaedam in Belgicum ſermonem eſſe tranſlata, quae magno uſui ſunt illis Eccleſiis &amp; Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiae ſtudioſis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nuper etiam inter nos Germanico idiomate editus libellus ex Anglico verſus de Prax Pietatis ità omnes afficit Pietatis Cultores, ut indè religioni quae in pura modeſtá<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis coelestis profeſſione conſiſtit, acceſſionem permagnam ſieri conſtet. Ideó<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſperare nobis licet, ſi huic noſtre vota accedat per vos favor requiſitus, ut facilè inter vestrates (qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ad haec &amp; ſimilia beneficia Eccleſiae ſuae praeſtanda prae aliis tranquillitatem in hiſce turbis, &amp; facultates conceſſiſſe videtur divina clementia) inveniantur aliqui, qui coll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendis, transferendis, digerendis, atque evulgandis Authorum praecipuis ſcriptis &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditationibus practicis non gravatè ſuas impendant operas, ſuum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> talentum ſi id ſuadebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis; unde futurum confidimus, ut inſigne Regnum Dei incrementum accipiat, ſi corpus ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutum talis doctrinae existet ex veſtris ſcriptoribus, in quo tam in Theologia Tyrones ſtudi</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:93868:4"/> 
                     <hi>ſui, quàm Eccleſiarum varii Paſtores Concionum ſuarum materiam invenire poſſint, aedifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationi multò utiliorem quàm illa eſt quae hodie in ſcriptis Polemicis occurrit: ità a ſtudio contentionis ad Charitatis non fictae affectus revocari poterunt multorum animi, ex quo tandem futurum ſit, ut ad Deum imprimis gloria &amp; gratiarum actio, ad Evangelii profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſores cum Sanctitatis &amp; Pietatis ſtudio, Pax &amp; Concordia, ad Eccleſias puplica aedifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, ad ſimpliciores pia Eruditio, ad pios afflictos, ſolida Spiritûs Conſolatio; ad errantes &amp; devios, ſalutaris Converſio; ad ſecuros &amp; carnales, vivida conſcientiae exuſcitatio; ad Hypocritas &amp; obſtinatos, clara perverſitatis ſuae convictio; ad omnes etiam poſteros, major lux veritatis perveniat; &amp; ad illos denique qui ſuum in hoc ſtudio Talentum collocabunt ad Regni Dci Promotionem, accedat illa vox quondam glorioſa &amp; beata à Domino, qui rationem accepti Talenti conferet nobiſcum, Bene eſt, Serve bone &amp; Fidelis, in exiguo fuiſti fidelis, ſuper multa te conſtituam: Ingredere in Gaudium Domini tui.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quod gaudium omnibus iis quibus postulatum hoc noſtrum pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp; gratum erit, cum omni corporali faelicitate ex animo vovemus. Valete in Domino Viri Excellentes, atque omni honore nobis colendi.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Dabantur</hi> Hanoviae <date>24. Febr. Anno 1633.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Joannes Daniel Wildius,</hi> Verbi Divin. Min. &amp; Eccleſiae <hi>Hanovicae</hi> Inſpector.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Theodorus Leurelius,</hi> Eccleſiae <hi>Hanovicae</hi> Miniſt.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Conradus Ammonius,</hi> Concionator Auli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Paulus Toſſanus,</hi> S. Theolog. D. &amp; Senatûs Eccleſiaſtici in inferiori <hi>Palatinatu</hi> Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorali Aſſeſſor.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Clemens Boeſius,</hi> Eccleſiae <hi>Gallicae Neo-Hanovicae</hi> Paſtor.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iſaacus Boots,</hi> Paſtor Eccleſiae <hi>Flandricae,</hi> quae Chriſto colligitur <hi>Hanoviae.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Matthaeus Rowyer,</hi> Eccleſiae <hi>Gallicae Neo-Han.</hi> Paſtor.</item>
                           <item>M. <hi>Philippus Pareus Davidis</hi> Filius, Illuſtris Gymnaſii <hi>Hanovienſis</hi> Rector &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Beſides theſe, who had a meeting in the City of <hi>Hanaw</hi> (whereunto I was called at the time above written, purpoſely to offer this Petition unto me, and to engage me to follow it for them) others there were, who having been made acquainted with this deſire of the forenamed Divines, did alſo joyn in the ſame ſuit by putting their hands to another Paper of the ſame Tenor at <hi>Herborn,</hi> and in ſome other places in <hi>March</hi> and <hi>April</hi> the ſame year 1633. Their names are theſe following:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Petrus Streithagen,</hi> Sereniſſ. Regis <hi>Bohemiae</hi> beatae memoriae Concionator. Aulicus.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Joh. Moriaen,</hi> V. Div. quondam apud <hi>Ubios</hi> Min. ſubſcripſi <hi>Francofurt,</hi> 23 <hi>April</hi> 1633.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Philippus Suabelius, Hoingae Solmenſis</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae Patriae Paſtor.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Johan. Conradus Hopifius,</hi> V. D. Miniſt. in Comitatu <hi>Hanov.</hi> in <hi>Marchabel.</hi> Exul. <hi>Palatin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Perutile hoe Propoſitum &amp; commune fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum <hi>Germanorum</hi> votum, meâ quoque ſubſcriptione confirmare volui ego <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus Meerbottius</hi> P. F. Paſtor <hi>Stresbeomi Ladenburgicus,</hi> in Elect. <hi>Palatinatu.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Johan. Irlin,</hi> Theol. Doct. Scholae <hi>Herbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis</hi> Rector &amp; Profeſſor, Eccleſiae ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Paſtor, &amp; Vicinarum <hi>Naſſovicarum</hi> Inſpector.</item>
                  <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Caſparus Stippius,</hi> Eccleſiae <hi>Siegenenſis</hi> Archidiaconus; qui ſuo &amp; reliquorum fratrum in Comitatu <hi>Naſſovico Siegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſi,</hi> nomine ſubſcripſit.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Johannes Arcularius,</hi> Eccleſiae <hi>Beilſteinſis</hi> Paſtor, qui ſuo &amp; reliquorum fratrum in Comitatu <hi>Naſſovico Beilstemenſi</hi> &amp; <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zenſi</hi> ſubſcripſit.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Dern,</hi> Paſtor <hi>Altenkirchenſis</hi> nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Eccleſiarum Comitatûs <hi>Sainenſis.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb facs="tcp:93868:4"/>
                  <head>This Letter in Engliſh ſpeaks thus: <hi>To the chief Patrons and Rulers of the Churches of Great</hi> Brittaine <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>the eminent ſervants of God, and moſt respected favourers of the diſtreſſed Church in</hi> Germany, <hi>be Grace and Peace from God the Father and our Lord</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>through the Communion of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Amen.</head>
                  <p>ALthough it is atteſted by the Holy Oracles, and the thing it ſelf doth ſpeak it that to the ſeverall Members of the Church, ſeverall gifts of Gods Spirit are beſtowed; yet it is evident, that the Father of Lights, the giver of every perfect gift, doth in the diſtribution of all his gifts, propoſe unto himſelf but one and the ſame end, which is the common edification and mutual uſefulneſs of all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to each other. For the Apoſtle ſaith, That the manifeſtation of the Spirit is given to every one to profit withall; and elſewhere we are commanded, As every one hath received the gift, even ſo to miniſter the ſame unto one another, as good Stewards of the manifold grace of God: For the Talent which every one of us have received of God, is committed to our truſt, that we being made diſtributers thereof, ſhould not hide it in the ground, as that unprofitable ſervant did, but employ it to the advantage of our Lord, that with ſuch ſervants as are faithfull unto him we may gain more Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, both to our Maſters uſe, and to our ſelves.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things, Illuſtrious and Renowned Gentlemen, Moſt Reverend and Reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Fathers and Brethren, are alledged, to the end that we may acquaint you with our wiſhes and deſires, that ſeeing we are certainly informed, that in the Churches of Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> the Doctrine of Practicall Divinity, by the publique Writings of many godly wiſe Miniſters of your Churches, is brought to a great perfection, and that it is excellently fitted for the uſe of the Common people, but yet kept up as an hidden Treaſure from the eyes of Forrein Nations, within the bounds of your own language alone; and that a very great benefit would accrue unto all Chriſtian Churches, and chiefly to thoſe that profeſſe the purity of the Goſpel, if ſo be thoſe things which are peculiar unto you were publiſhed, ſo as by them they might alſo be read and underſtood: Seeing (we ſay) theſe things are ſo, our purpoſe is to acquaint your Honours and Worſhips with our wiſhes and deſires; and by the bond of holy Communion in Chriſt, and with that confidence of ſpeech which our brotherly free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom doth ſuggeſt, to intreat you (you chiefly who being Rulers, Protectors and Favourers of the Churches, and are truly deſirous to edifie the publique) that ye would not ſuffer ſo precious a Talent to be hid and concealed any longer from the hands and eyes of Forreiners; but that ye would, according to the pious zeal and affection of fervent Charity which ye have toward your Brother-Churches, and the bountifull care which ye have for the Glory of God in the propagation of the Goſpel, take ſome convenient courſe, by which the Marrow of theſe Authors, which in that kind are exſtant amongſt you, and are of chief Note, may be gathered out of all into one Volume, either of Common places, or of a body of Practicall Divinity, which may be publiſhed and made uſe of by all in a tongue known and common to the learned.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:93868:5"/>
                  <p>We have heard that ſome few things have been tranſlated into the low <hi>Dutch</hi> lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, which are of great uſe unto thoſe Churches, and their Schollars of Divinity.</p>
                  <p>Of late alſo there is a little Book of the <hi>Practiſe of Piety,</hi> tranſlated out of Engliſh into our <hi>Germane</hi> tongue, which hath taken ſo much with many godly ſouls, that we find thereby wrought in them a very great growth of that Religious diſpoſition, which doth conſiſt in a pure and modeſt Profeſſion of heavenly truth; for which cauſe we do hope, that if our wiſhes may obtain by your means the favour which is deſired, that ſome of your Men (to whom God ſeemeth mercifully to have given in the midſt of theſe troubles, both quietneſſe and means to conferre theſe and ſuch like benefits unto his Church) will eaſily be found, who without difficulty will at your perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, beſtow their pains and their Talents, to Collect, to Tranſlate, to Digeſt, and to publiſh the chief practical Writings and Meditations of your Authors. Whence we are confident this will come to paſſe, that the Kingdom of God will receive a notable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement, if a compleat Body of ſuch Doctrine out of your Writers were put forth; wherein, as well the young Schollars of Divinity for their Studies, as many Paſtors of the Churches for their Sermons, might find matter far more uſefull unto edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then that is, which now adaies is met withall in Controverſal Writings. So that by this means, the minds of many men may be drawn back from the endeavours of ſtrife, unto the affections of unfained Charity; whence afterward this will follow, that unto God in the firſt place, Glory and thankſgiving will redound; and then unto the Profeſſors of the Goſpel, with the care of holineſſe and piety, peace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, to the Churches, publique Edification; to the ſimple ſort, pious learning; to the godly and afflicted, ſound ſpirituall comfort; to the erring, and ſuch as go aſtray, ſaving Converſion; to ſuch as are ſecure and carnall, a lively wakening of their Conſcience; to the Hypocrites and ſtubborn ſinners, a clear diſcovery of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſs; and to all the Generations to come, a greater light of truth will be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced: and laſtly, unto thoſe that ſhall beſtow their Talent towards this endeavour for the advancement of Gods Kingdom, when he ſhall call us to an account of the Talent which we have received from him, that glorious and bleſſed voyce ſhall then come from the Lord unto them, <hi>Well done thou good and faithfull ſervant, thou haſt been faithfull in a few things, I will make thee Ruler over many things; enter into the joy of thy Lord:</hi> which joy we wiſh from our heart, together with all temporal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to all thoſe to whom our requeſt ſhall be made known, and with whom it ſhall find acceptance.</p>
                  <p>Farewell in the Lord excellent Gentlemen, whom with all reſpect we are bound to worſhip.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given at <hi>Hanaw</hi> 
                        <date>24. <hi>Febr. Anno</hi> 1633.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>By
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Daniel Wildius,</hi> Miniſter of Gods Word, and Inſpector of the Churches of <hi>Hanaw.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Theodorus Leurelius,</hi> Preacher of the Church of <hi>Hanaw.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Conradus Ammonius,</hi> Preacher to the Court of the ſame place.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Paulus Toſſanus,</hi> Doctor in Divinity, &amp; an Aſſeſſor of the Eccleſiaſtical Senate in the lower Electoral Palatinat.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Clemens Boeſius,</hi> Paſtor of the <hi>French</hi> Church in <hi>New Hanaw.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iſaacus Boots,</hi> Paſtor of the <hi>Flanders</hi> Church, which is gathered unto Chriſt in <hi>Hanaw.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Matthew Rowyer,</hi> Paſtor of the <hi>French</hi> Church at <hi>New Hanaw.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>M. <hi>Philippus Pareus,</hi> Son to <hi>David,</hi> Rector and Profeſſor of the famous Colledge of <hi>Hanaw.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:93868:5"/>
               <head>At <hi>Herborne</hi> in <hi>March,</hi> and elſewhere in <hi>April,</hi> in the ſame year 1633. the ſame ſute was renewed by theſe:</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Petrus Streithagen,</hi> Preacher to the Court of the moſt Illuſtrious King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> of bleſſed Memory.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Moriaen,</hi> formerly Preacher of Gods Word amongſt thoſe of <hi>Collen.</hi> I did underwrite this at <hi>Francofurt,</hi> 23 <hi>April, Anno</hi> 1633.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Philip Suabelius,</hi> of <hi>Hoing,</hi> in the County of <hi>Solms,</hi> Preacher to his Native Church.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Conradus Hopiſius,</hi> Miniſter of the Word of God in the County of <hi>Hanaw</hi> in <hi>Mercabel</hi> an exiled Palatin.</item>
               <item>I <hi>Henry Mecrobottius,</hi> for the preſent time Paſtor of <hi>Scheſheim Ladenburg</hi> in the Electoral Palatinat, am willing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm alſo with my Subſcription, this moſt profitable intention and common wiſh of our Brethren of <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Irlin,</hi> Doctor of Divinity, Rector and Profeſſor of the School of <hi>Herbon,</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor of the Church of the ſame place, and Inſpector of the neighbouring Churches of <hi>Naſſaw.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Caſparus Stippius</hi> Arch-Deacon of the Church of <hi>Siegen,</hi> who ſubſcribed in his own name, and in the name of the reſt of his Brethren, in the County of <hi>Sie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> in <hi>Naſſaw.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Arcularius,</hi> Paſtor of the Church of <hi>Beilſtein,</hi> who ſubſcribed in his own name, and in the name of the reſt of his Brethren in the Counties of <hi>Beilſtein</hi> &amp; <hi>Ozen</hi> in <hi>Naſſaw.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Dern.</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Altenkirch,</hi> in the name of the Churches of the County of <hi>Sainen.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>THis Letter doth ſufficiently ſpeak for it ſelf; and the perſons who did offer it, were in thoſe parts none of the leaſt conſiderable Proteſtants, nor is their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſmall, if you take notice of the Churches in whoſe name ſome have ſubſcribed: and although the time ſince it was offered, may ſeem ſomewhat long yet becauſe that which hitherto could be done to obtain their deſire, hath not been neglected, though by ſeveral invincible impediments obſtructed, becauſe the expectation of obtaining it, is not vaniſhed, but at this time raiſed: and becauſe ſuch a ſuit as this can never be out of date till it be fulfilled; nay although the firſt Petitioners ſhould all be dead, it ought not the leſſe conſcienably to be regarded by thoſe to whom it is made, becauſe it doth not at all concern any temporal, or ſo much the particular conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of thoſe that make it, as the ſpiritual edification, and general benefit of all the Churches of God, and of the ages to come in the Goſpel. I ſay, becauſe of all theſe conſiderations, and more that might be added, therefore I am willing to ſecond their requeſt, as I am many waies bound to do; and to that effect, I ſhall firſt ſhew my ſenſe of the Body of Divinity, which I conceive will ſatisfie their demand; and then the Reaſons why it ought to be, and manner how it may be made up.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93868:6"/>
               <head>Of the Firſt.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>What is meant by a Body of Practicall Divinity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y Practicall Divinity, is meant the revealed truths of God, concerning the obedience of the faith which is to be yielded unto his will.</p>
               <p>There is a two-fold Divine Truth; the one is to be contemplated, which is the Object of the Underſtanding and Remembrance; the other is to be practiſed, which is the Object of the Will and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. The firſt, as we partake of it, is the Conformity of our Intellectuall faculty to the teſtimony of Gods Word, when we conceive aright of his meaning therein. The ſecond, as we par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. 1. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. 16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 1, 2.</note> of it, is the Conformity of the purpoſes of our heart, to that which is known to be Gods will, when we prove how good, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and acceptable it is. That firſt, is in the Notions of the Mind to beget Knowledge: This other, is in the Conviction of the Conſcience, to beget Reſolutions and obediential Performance. Of the firſt ſort of truth, Chriſt ſaith, <hi>If ye continue in my Word, ye ſhall know the truth,</hi> Joh. 8. 31, 32. Of the ſecond, he ſaith, <hi>He that doth truth, cometh to the light,</hi> Joh. 3. 21. So then as there is a contemplative and intelligible, ſo there is a Practicable truth, that is a truth to be done, which is the action of Vertue: for Chriſt in <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. <hi>v</hi> 20 21. doth oppoſe the doing of evil, and the doing of truth; that is Vice and Vertue to one another: He ſaith, <hi>every one that doth evil</hi> (that is, who is vicious in his life) <hi>hateth the light; but he that doth truth,</hi> (that is, whoſe life is vertuous and upright) <hi>commeth to the light.</hi> As darkneſſe is to light, ſo truth is oppoſite to all falſhood; not only to that of ignorance and errour, but eſpecially to that of lying and deceitfulneſs, which are no leſs inſeparable compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of vice, then ſincerity and uprightneſs are of vertue in the ſouls of men.</p>
               <p>Now both the Intellectual and Practical truth, is originally exiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt in the living word, as in the principle and fountain; and from thence by the teſtimony of Jeſus, which is the Spirit of Propheſie in the Scriptures, it is derived unto us, as to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle and veſſel, when by it we are ſanctified, according to Chriſt's Prayer, <hi>John</hi> 17 17. <hi>Sanctifie them in thy truth, thy Word is truth;</hi> the Word preached by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Prophets, is both exhorting and teſtifying; that is, both Practical and Theoretical concerning that truth which in God is eſſential; but as it is manifeſted to us, it is the Grace of God which bringeth ſalvation, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 11. Hence it is, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ought, or may be called Theology, but that which is taught by the Divine Oracles: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> can only furniſh us with that knowledge which is true Theology; and whether it be in the Theoretical or Practical matters, nothing is true Divinity, but that which is Divine truth; nor is any thing a Divine truth, but that which is manifeſted by the Word of God: the Word then to us, is the Standard of Truth.</p>
               <p>Now although the Action of the underſtanding, muſt of neceſſity be Antecedent to all our Acts of truth, becauſe the will is a knowing faculty, and cannot act order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without the Underſtanding; yet the Theoretical truths notionally apprehended,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93868:6"/> bring the ſoul to no perfection of happineſs, except they become fruitfull in the actions of vertue. The Notional Science of all Gods truth, and of his whole will, as it may be in the brain alone, and without the practice whereunto that Science doth oblige the heart, is more hurtfull then profitable to our felicity; It had been better (ſaith <hi>Peter) not to have known the way of righteouſneſſe, then</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 21. <hi>John</hi> 3. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>after they have known it, to turn from the holy Commandment. If ye know theſe things</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>happy are ye if ye do them:</hi> whence it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that if ye do them not, you are not happy, although you know them. And the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> doth place the bleſſedneſs of a man in his Deed, as diſtinct from his bare knowledge, when he ſaith, <hi>He that is not a</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 21, 25.</note> 
                  <hi>hearer of the Word only, but a doer of the Work, this man ſhall be bleſſed in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eed:</hi> The happineſs of his condition is made perfect in his Deed. Whence it is evident, that Practicall truths import us and reach our hapineſſe more neerly then Theoreticall; becauſe that which wee know, although it be a truth, is no part of our felicity, nor a true bleſſing of God unto us, except it either bring forth an injoyment of the life of God in us, or elſe reſult from that enjoyment to us: for the ſubſtance of all our felicity unto all eternity, is nothing elſe but our union with God, which is the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of his life; and this life is only enjoyed then when by his truth he liveth in us, and we in him.) His life in us, is ſpiritual light and power: Light is in the underſtanding; and power is to move conformably to Gods will in the whole inward Man: The Light ſheweth him to us, the Power maketh us and him one; we may know him at a diſtance, but we cannot feel his life, and move in him, except he be in us, and we one with him. The knowledge therefore hath leſs of the enjoyment then the power of life but there is a two-fold knowledg of Gods truth; The one goeth before the enjoyment of his life, and the other followeth upon it. The knowledge which goeth before the enjoyment of Gods life, is the true light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 9. &amp; this light is that which may be known of God, which he doth manifeſt in Men, and ſheweth unto them: He doth manifeſt in Men, both that which doth make them clearly ſee his eternal power and God-head, ſo that they are without excuſe; and that alſo which maketh them ſhew the work of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 19, 20. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 15.</note> his Law written in their hearts. All this is manifeſted in them, and ſhewed unto them, partly by the Creation of the World, partly by their own Conſcience; but yet all this, and much more then this, revealed both in the Law given to the Jews, and in the Goſpel, given both to Jews and Gentiles: I ſay, all this both naturall which is common, and ſupernaturall, which is ſpecially re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed knowledge; nay although it might be in ſuch a high degree, as to manifeſt all Myſteries unto them, may be fruitleſſe: and he that hath it without bleſſedneſs, and deſtitute of the life of God: for the truth which is both manifeſted in the natural mans heart, and ſhewed unto him by the Creation, is held up by him in unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 18. And although he doth know God, yet he glorifieth him not as God, <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. And the Jews which had the form of knowledge in the Law, and could teach others, did not practiſe that which they taught; but by their tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Law, they did diſhonour God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 21, 22, 23. And the Gentiles to whom, together with the Jews, the light of the Goſpel was and is revealed, ſhall be condemned becauſe they loved darkneſs rather then light, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 19. And he that may know all Myſteries, may yet want Charity, and be nothing as to the happineſs and life of God. But although all this knowledge of Truth, which is Antecedent to the enjoyment of the life of God, may be void of the practiſe of Truth, and ſo come ſhort of happineſſe; yet it may alſo, through the practiſe of Truth, become effectuall unto
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93868:7"/> happineſs, if God make it fruitfull, which he doth according to his own pleaſure, in giving ſaving faith; whereby the heart is purified, that it may become obedient to all his will, by which means the ſoul partaketh of the life of God, and becometh truly happy: This knowledge then doth not otherwiſe make us happy, but as it bringeth us unto this eſtate.</p>
               <p>As for the other knowledge of Gods Truth, which followeth upon our union with him; it is nothing elſe but a further confirmation of the ſoul, in the truth which it hath received unto life, and an enlargement thereof by the enjoyment of God in his power; for Chriſt doth give us two promiſes to that effect: The firſt is, that by the truth of obedience, we ſhall come to the clearing of doubts, concerning intellectual matters, for <hi>Joh</hi> 7 <hi>v.</hi> 17. he ſaith, <hi>If any man will do the will of him that ſent me, he ſhall know of the Doctrine, whether it be of God, or whether I ſpeak of my ſelf.</hi> And the ſecond is, that upon the keeping of the Commandments, both the Father and the Sonne will manifeſt unto the ſoul which loveth them, their preſence in love. For Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 21, 23. <hi>He that hath my Commandments, and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me; and he that loveth me, ſhall be loved of my Father, and I will love him, and manifeſt my love unto him: and if any man love me, he will keep my words: and my Father will love him, and we will come unto him, and make our abode with him.</hi> Here the manifeſtation of Gods preſence, which is both the light and power of life unto the ſoul, is the conſequent of the obedience of faith: and ſo it is in that of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>John,</hi> 1 <hi>Epiſt. Chap.</hi> 5. 20. <hi>And we know that the Son of God is come, and hath given us an underſtanding, that we may know him that is true, and we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt; this is the true God and eternall life.</hi> This is a reflexive know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge from God upon our ſelves, in the enjoyment of him as our happineſs; and ſo is that, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 14. <hi>We know that we have paſſed from death to life, becauſe we love the brethren.</hi> So then we ſee, that all truth, as it is the object of contemplation, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a Preparative to, or a conſequent of the Truth, which is the object of Action. The Practicall truth then is the main thing to be heeded, for to it the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical is either ſubſervient and ſubordinate, or a neceſſary and infallible effect. The Apoſtle maketh this evident by the nature of his Miniſtry, which <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 1. (he ſaith) <hi>Is to be an Apoſtle according to the faith of Gods Elect, and the acknowledgment of the truth which is after Godlineſſe:</hi> Intimating clearly, that as his Apoſtle-ſhip was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God to beget faith in the Elect, by their acknowledgment of the truth; ſo the acknowledgment of the truth and faith, is appointed to beget the life of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Believers. Therefore as the end and perfection of his Apoſtleſhip was the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting of faith by the acknowledgment of the truth; nor was he warranted to teach or do any thing, which did not tend to that end and effect: So the end and perfection of all true knowledge, is the life of Godlineſſe; nor is any knowledge in ſpirituall things warrantable, or any thing to be accounted a truth, which doth not tend to this end and effect. Godlineſs therefore, which is the practiſe of divine Truth, is the meaſure of all intellectuall truths; for whatſoever matter of knowledge is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionate, ſubordinate, and ſubſervient unto the production of the life of God in the ſoul of a Beleever, is not to be received as a divine Truth; for the faith of Gods Elect, is in the acknowledgement of none other truth, but of that which is after Godlineſſe.</p>
               <p>From all which we ſhall inferre this Concluſion; That the ſtudy of Practical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, is of farre greater concernment unto all, and far more to be heeded, eſteemed, and entertained in the Schools of the Prophets; then the ſtudy of contemplative My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries and notions of Divinity; whereupon Controverſal matters are ordinarily at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93868:7"/> And ſeeing there are ſo many bodies and Syſtemes of Theoretical and Controverſal matters, that it would be no eaſie task to any man to reckon them all up; and yet there is not ſo much as one compleat body or Syſteme of Practical Divinity found in all the Churches; whereunto we ſee nevertheleſs, that all Theoretical Truths ought to be referred, &amp; directed as to their end; it is evident that therein there is a manifeſt defect, and that much is wanting hereby, to the increaſe of publique Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, to the ſupply of ſpiritual Conſolation, and to the ſettlement of a ſound Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in all the Churches, which may be remedied by a Body of this nature.</p>
               <p>Now by this which we call a Body of Divinity, is meant a full Collection, and an orderly diſpoſition of all divine Truths which are after godlineſs, under ſeveral diſtinct heads and matters; to the end that from the holy Scriptures, the man of God may be perfectly inſtructed, and throughly furniſhed with ſufficient helps and directions, which by the Spirit of Faith, may not onely make him wiſe unto ſalvation, but able alſo to work all his works in God.</p>
               <p>And concerning this Body, Seeing I am intruſted and conſcionably obliged, as in the preſence of God, to ſolicite the ſame towards thoſe that are able to contribute their Talents to make it up; I conceive it may be an advantage to the Work, to offer up the parts thereof unto their conſideration, that the number of tasks being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed and known, ſuch as God ſhall inable and ſtir up to manifeſt his truth, and to joyn with others in compleating this work may know what tasks to chuſe, and how to concurre with each other in elaborating the ſame.</p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore with due reſpect unto better judgements, offer theſe following thoughts unto ſuch as ſhall be undertakers in this Work.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I lay this Fundamental Rule to be obſerved in the contrivance of the whole, and of every part of the Work, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Number and Meaſure of the Parts of this Bodie ſhould be made ſutable and proportionate to the end thereof: that as nothing ſhould be brought into it, which is not proper and uſeful to the attainment of the end, ſo nothing ſhould be left out which may be requiſite and ſubſervient there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
               <p>We ſhall therefore look upon the end and uſe of the Work, that we may find the parts thereof without defect, and without ſuperfluity.</p>
               <p>The truth of Godlineſs, which is the Object of Practical Divinitie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; is the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the life of God. The aime for which this Truth is to be atteſted unto the world, and practiſed by ſuch as know and believe it; is that we may enjoy God by partaking of his life in the divine nature, having eſcaped the corruption which is in the world through luſt, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4.</p>
               <p>This life of God in the divine nature, is communicable unto us by none other means, but by the knowledge of Chriſt, and the truth which is in him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 6, 7, 8, 9. and 7. 3. <hi>Eph</hi> 4. 18, 19, 20, 21. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3. 10. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 2, 3.</p>
               <p>And that which Chriſt doth communicate unto us of this life, is made perceptible unto us by two properties of Life wrought in us, the one is the Light, the other is the power of life: By the light of life, we are made wiſe unto ſalvation: and by the power of life, wee are enabled to worke out our ſalvation, that is, to do all our workes in God. This then is the compleat end of practical Divinity, to teach men the wiſdome which is profitable unto the ſalvation of their ſouls, and the direction of the whole converſation to Gods will, that they may be enabled whatever they do, to do all in God by walking in his light: and what Doctrine ſoever doth not directly tend unto this end, is no part of this Body, and ought not to be mentioned in it, but whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver doth thus tend thereunto, ought not to be omitted.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93868:8"/>
               <p>To deliver then all, and neither more nor leſſe, then all the Doctrines and truths which may directly be helpful to advance a man unto the attainement of this end; I conceive that this body of Divinity ſhould be made up of two Generall parts. The firſt, containing the poſitive and undeniable Truths. The ſecond, the doubtful caſes of Conſcience concerning the practiſe of Godlineſs. That part which is poſitive, ſhould contain concerning the life of Godlines, three things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, The Precognitions to prepare the mind to think of that life.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The Principles by which that life is begotten.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The Parts or Acts, wherein that life doth conſiſt.</p>
               <p>By the Precognitions, I mean ſuch truths as muſt be taken notice of, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, or at leaſt not contradicted and doubted of, before the Doctrine of Godlineſs can be taught, and without the acknowledgement of which, no man can be rationally dealt withall, or induced to intend to live unto God according to his revealed will.</p>
               <p>By the Principles of the life of Godlineſs, I mean the Fundamentall Doctrines of divine Truth, which begetteth love unto God, and thereby obligeth the conſcience unto all dutifulneſſe of obedience towards him.</p>
               <p>By the Parts and acts, wherein the life of Godlineſſe doth conſiſt, I mean all things which either ſubſtantially or circumſtantially belong thereunto to make it up, as the ſtate of the Perfect man in God.</p>
               <p>By the Subſtantials of this life, I mean two things. Firſt, All truths which diſcover the inward frame and regeneration of the ſoul which liveth the life of God. Secondly, All truths which hold forth the outward frame; the way of walking and the work of the Profeſſion which is proper to that life, and inſeparable from the ends thereof.</p>
               <p>By the Circumſtantials of the life of Godlineſſe, I underſtand all the different out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtates and particular callings of Profeſſors, wherein God doth ſet people in this life; as of Husband and Wife, Father and Child, Maſter and Servant; of Magiſtrate and Subject, of Paſtor and flock, and ſuch like; To all which ſeverall duties belong, and thereunto ſeveral directions are accordingly to be given, to ſhew how every one ſhould walk in all truth with a good Conſcience before God and Man. In this diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of truths we may find, concerning the Tree of life, as it were the foyl prepared before it be Planted, in the Precognitions; the Root, which is to be Planted in the Principles; the Stemme, when it is grown up in the Subſtantials; and the branches, after the full growth in the Circumſtantials of the way of Godlineſſe; ſo that in this Body of Divinity, the man of God ſhould be compleated and ſet forth. Firſt, As it were in his Head and Intellectuals, by the Recognitions and Principles. Secondly, In his heart and vital Motions, by the Subſtantials: And laſtly, In his Limbs and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Members, without which he is not a compleat man, by the Circumſtantials of his life: and as none of theſe parts, or of the things neceſſary to make up the ſame ſhould be wanting in this Body; ſo the matters belonging to each of theſe heads ought to be delivered fully, yet not ſuperfluouſly; that is to ſay, ſo as they ſhould not only contain the Marrow, but the fleſh and full ſubſtance of all profitable truths; yet without need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Repetitions, large Amplifications, Retorical Digreſſions and enlargements, which to move mens affections, rather then to convince their Conſcience, and inlighten their underſtandings, are frequently uſed by writers of Practicall Matters.</p>
               <p>And as theſe Generall parts of the whole Body ought thus to follow one another, in reſpect of their naturall dependance upon each other; ſo the matters ſubordinate unto every one of theſe, ought to be ſet in a method, which is poſitive and proper to their nature, that there may be a coherence of all the parcels in the whole, without any redundancy.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:93868:8"/>
               <p>And although ſuch a Body of truths fully and clearly delivered, might ſuffice to Men that are free from all prejudice and of able parts, to direct them in all Caſes of Practiſe, which may be incident to the Courſe of their life; yet becauſe the work is not to be compiled for them alone, but for others alſo; and becauſe many doubts and ſcruples of Conſcience are and will be raiſed, partly by the weakneſſe of ſome, partly by the malice of others, which every ordinary capacity is not, and will not be able readily to reſolve by it ſelfe, although it be helped with the undoubted Principles, with the ſtanding Truths, and with the rules of practiſe, which ſuch a compleat Bodie of Divinitie may containe: therefore to ſupply this defect of knowledge, (which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though but accidental, yet is unavoidable) an appendix or Supplement of ſpecial doubts and caſes of conſcience (for I ſuppoſe the common doubts, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as are incident to meer natural men, will be cleared by the Doctrine of the Body it ſelf) ſhould be added unto the Body in a method relating the order of Matters, delivered in each part where the ground of the deciſion of the doubtful caſe is to be found: And if this be done, I cannot ſee what could be deſired, or further wiſhed for in this kind; only to make this Appendix of caſe-Divinity compleat (becauſe caſes according to the differences of Mens capacities and apprehenſions of matters, may be as to us innumerable,) therefore ſome general Rules before the particular caſes be ſet down, ſhould be given, to direct the wavering mind of what degree of proficiencie ſoever, how to order it ſelf in ſeeking out by the teſtimonies of the Scripture, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted tenour of the Covenant within its own heart; a determination of any que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion whatſoever, at leaſt ſo farre, that it ſhould not be able to perplex the ſpirit with any unſettlement in the grounds of Faith, Hope, and Love, which are the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of our whole profeſſion in this life. For by the confidence of Faith, we ſtand and reſt in reſpect of God; by the joyfulneſs of Hope, in reſpect <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 6. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 14. <hi>&amp; Rom.</hi> 13. 8, 9.</note> of our ſelves; and by the ſincerity of Love, in reſpect of our Neighbour; Theſe general Directions then ſhould firſt be delivered with an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in a caſe or two, how to uſe them, &amp; then the particular caſes which have ſome difficulty more then ordinary ſhould be brought in and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved.</p>
               <p>Thus we have the many Heads of the whole; but this will not ſuffice for a diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of particular Tasks, becauſe each Head is too comprehenſive; there muſt be a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſion of every part by it ſelf, into its parcels, ſet in order like unto the Anatomy or Sceleton of a mans body, wherein all the bones do hang one upon another; ſo that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the number of parts, the talneſs of each part, &amp; the place thereof in the body may be diſcerned: And although ſuch a delineation as this of bare bones, will have no life in it, and be only like the rude draught of a Painter before he puts colours to his work; yet it may be not onely uſeful, but will be even neceſſary to make the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the body appeare, which afterwards may have life put to it.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Concerning the Precognitions.</head>
                  <p>GOd having made man a rational Creature, doth ſtill rule him, and in all his wayes towards him, doth walk with him according to the grounds of that Reaſon which he at firſt gave him; and although through his defection from God (in whoſe light alone he could ſee light) by his own default and free choice of earthly-mindedneſs, he hath darkened the eye of his underſtanding, and made himſelf blind both in the things which are ſupernatural, and alſo in very many things which are natural; ſo that in reſpect of theſe he hath not any true Notions at all,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93868:9"/> till they be renewed in him; and in reſpect of theſe, the Notions which he hath, he cannot improve ſo, as to apply them by himſelf towards their right ends, without ſome ſpecial directory and help: yet it cannot be truly ſaid, that God hath left Man deſtitute of all light, and without all Teſtimony of the being of things ſupernatural, and of the right improvement of things natural; for he doth ſtill maintain ſome gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Principles and Inſtincts, as glimmerings of his truth within him, to the end that he may not onely be without excuſe in reſpect of his back-ſliding, but that he may be made a ſubject capable of Grace through the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> to be reſtored to his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal integrity, when he ſhall be rationally dealt withal, both by the remainder of the light which he hath, and in that which is to be ſuper-added thereunto; for I ſhall freely acknowledge (yet without any advantage to <hi>Socinian</hi> Principles) that God doth oblige no man to entertain any thought, either of ſpiritual or natural things, or of his own dealings with man-kind in the one or the other way, which is contrary to found Reaſon; but that every one who will either conceive of God rightly, or live unto him juſtly, is obliged to do it in a rational way, both in reference to God, and toward Men, becauſe we are commanded to be ready to give a reaſon of the hope which is in us, to every one that asketh it of us, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 15. and to preſent our body a living ſacrifice, holy and acceptable unto God, by our reaſonable ſervice, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 1. And although in this place <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> may be rendred a ſervice according to his Word, as <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 2. is well rendred the ſincere Milk of the Word; yet becauſe the Word of God did by Wiſdome create all things at firſt, and ſtill doth uphold all things as they were created, it muſt needs be rational in it ſelf, and to all intellectual Creatures, the original cauſe of all Reaſon, becauſe every Truth and Precept of duty revealed to man therein, is by the Scriptures rationally offered to the Conſcience of thoſe that are taught of God thereby; and becauſe they that are taught, are bound to take notice of the reaſons why they beleeve and do every thing, ſo as to be able to give a rational account thereof unto other reaſonable Men, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the one, and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the other place, are to be underſtood in the fulneſſe of their ſignification, as they comprehend both the Notions of Rationality, and of the Word of God, which indeed are inſeparable; for as it cannot be imagined, that Gods Word ſhould have been ſeparate from his Wiſdom, ſo we ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that his Wiſdom and Will expreſſed in his Word concerning every thing, is that truth of being and reality of reaſon which is extant in it; and that which in our mind is by any thing found a truth, and found reaſon convincing our Conſcience, is his Word by that thing towards us.</p>
                  <p>And this obſervation I have premiſed to that which I am about to offer, concerning the Precognitions of the life of Godlineſſe; leſt I might ſeem to deſire without a juſt cauſe and ſufficient motive, that which I ſhall propoſe as a task to the workmen to be compleated, before any thing elſe can be fruitfully and by a rational man (to whom our addreſſes muſt be made in this undertaking) convincingly entertained.</p>
                  <p>For before any mans underſtanding can be dealt withall, to induce him to live unto God according to his will he muſt be brought to acknowledge that God is, and that the life of man may have ſome reference unto him by the knowledge of his will. Therefore theſe things before all others muſt be rationally made out unto him: and to this effect, four Heads of truth ought to be handled ſatisfactorily, which are theſe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, That there is a God.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, That God is to be feared, worſhipped, and glorified by Man; and that he is a rewarder of thoſe that fear, worſhip and glorifie him.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, That the Scriptures given to the Jewiſh Church of old by the Prophets,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93868:9"/> and to the Churches of the Gentiles and Jews by the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles, are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly Gods Word.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, That the Scriptures were given by thoſe Men, to teach all men the true way of fearing, worſhipping and glorifying God.</p>
                  <p>Theſe truths ought to be cleared upon the ground of common Reaſon, which all men are ſuppoſed to be made capable of; and to this effect, I ſuppoſe it will be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to handle theſe following, or ſuch like Poſitions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the Firſt, <hi>That there is a God.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TO Demonſtrate unto a Rational man that there is a God, he muſt be made to acknowledge theſe following truths.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That in this World, beſides the things which are viſible, there be other things inviſible; which though concealed from ſenſe, have a being, and may be underſtood to be.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the Heavens, the Earth, and the things viſible therein, have not their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from themſelves, but from ſomething elſe which is not ſeen, but may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood to be over all, as the Governour and ſupream power thereof, which is called God.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That this ſupream power is before all things, without beginning and ending; infinite in all perfections, moſt wiſe, good and bountiful in giving all things unto all.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That amongſt all viſible things, as Man is the moſt perfect; ſo he can leaſt of all have his Being from inferiour Creatures, or from himſelf: but having it from the ſupream cauſe, more remarkably then other Creatures, he is more enabled then they to know God and reſpect him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the Second.</head>
                  <p>VVHen upon theſe grounds a man is Convicted that there is a God; then to demonſtrate unto him rationally, that this God ought to be feared, worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and glorified by Man-kind; theſe following, or ſuch like Poſitions, are to be made out unto him.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That Man hath a ſoul endowed with a Reaſoning facultie, whereby he is able to judge of his own actions, and know his own aims, though ſecret and hidden from others.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That in this judging facultie, there is ſomething which univerſally in all ages Men have called Conſcience, which ſecretly accuſeth, or elſe excuſeth Men concerning their actions and aims, chiefly when others judge of them otherwiſe then they meant them.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That this Conſcience doth bear witneſſe unto all men (in whom it is awake) from their own reaſon, that they are under the power of God, and that they ought to be thankful to God.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That the reaſon which convicteth mens Conſcience that they are under God, will alſo convict them, that they ought to ſhew their thankfulneſs unto God, ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly unto the nature and properties of Gods being, and not otherwiſe.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. That the nature and propertie of Gods being, ſeeing in all things it is the firſt and ſupream, is in it ſelf infinitely perfect, and to all other things the alone Author
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93868:10"/> of all good; and that therefore it ought to have the glory of this ſupremacie, perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and goodneſſe, given unto it by man in his uſe of all things.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. That in caſe he doth not ſhew himſelfe thankful by reſpecting the glorie due to God in all things, he doth then deſerve to be caſt off by God, and deprived of the fruit of his goodneſſe in all things.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. That it a man doth give unto God the glory which is due to his Name, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thankfull unto him; he may aſſure himſelfe, that God, as he is wiſe and all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing, will take notice of him; and as he is juſt and good, will be mercifull and beneficiall unto him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the Third.</head>
                  <p>WHen a Man hath acknowledged theſe truths, that there is a God, and that he is to be glorified by Man anſwerably to the properties of his nature; then we muſt rationally induce him to believe, that the Scriptures written to Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, by the Prophets, Evangeliſts and Apoſtles, are the Word of God: And this may be done by the demonſtration of theſe or the like Poſitions.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That no Books in the World have greater evidences and arguments of truth, in reſpect of their Hiſtory, then theſe have: two things muſt be made out. 1. That they were written by thoſe Men, by whom they are ſaid to be written. 2. That the Matters of fact recorded in them, are as rationally credible, as any other humane Records whatſoever.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the Writers of thoſe Books (whatſoever they were) were undoubtedly the true ſervants of God, inſpired by him in writing the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That all the Doctrines and Precepts of divine fear and worſhip contained there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, are moſt ſutable to the nature and property of Gods Supremacy, Perfection and goodneſſe; and that they are more anſwerable unto the true Notions of duty written in the heart of Mankind towards God, then the Doctrines and Precepts of any other Book and Religion whatſoever extant any where in all the World.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the Fourth.</head>
                  <p>VVHen a Man is rationally Convicted, or at leaſt induced to believe that there is no cauſe to contradict this truth, that the Scriptures are the Word of God; it will be no difficult matter to let him ſee by the ſubſtance of the matters contained therein, and the ends for which they were written and given both to the Jews and Gentiles; that they were written and given to no other end, but to teach all Men the true way of fearing, worſhipping, and glorifying God: And to this effect, theſe or ſuch like Poſitions may be made out.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the whole ſumme and ſubſtance of the Hiſtory of the Bible doth directly tend to this ſcope.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the Authors of the Holy Scriptures, do expreſly declare this to be the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of their writing.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That the naturall Properties and effects of the things taught by them, and their manner of teaching the ſame, are wholly fitted to work upon the ſpirits of men, thoſe impreſſions and affections which lead them to feare, worſhip, and glorifie God.</p>
                  <p>To all which, this Poſition at laſt ſhould be added.</p>
                  <p>That there ſhall be a time wherein God will judge men according to the works wherein they have, or have not feared, worſhipped, and glorified God: which is to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93868:10"/> be made out upon three Grounds, which may be rationally evinced.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe God having made all things under a Law, and Ruling all Men by a Law of Reaſon; muſt needs alſo be acknowledged as a Judge over the obſervers and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors of his Laws, and conſequently have a time to exerciſe his judgement.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the rational Souls of Men are immortal, and live when they are ſeparated from the bodie, and conſequently can undergo a judgement after this life.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That the Conſciences of Men bearing witneſſe to them of their wicked deeds, even againſt their wills, though they live in outward proſperitie, put them in fear; and bearing witneſſe alſo of the vertuous deeds of good Men, though they are in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward adverſity, yet comfort and ſupport them; which inward teſtimonies of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of Men are not vain notions, but undeniable Evidences of a Judgement to come, which the Soul within it ſelf is ſenſible of.</p>
                  <p>When theſe things are thoroughly handled, and all Scruples which may be raiſed concerning the ſame are taken away, ſo that a Rational man, who is without preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, ſhall have no cauſe for want of the diſcovery of truths of this nature to make any further doubt thereof; I ſuppoſe the ground is prepared upon which the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals of Divine Faith, that is, the Doctrine of Revealed Truths (which by natural Reaſoning no man can reach unto) may be offered. For as God doth make a man firſt by a living ſoul to be a natural man, and afterward he becomes by grace a new creature and ſpirituall man: ſo I ſuppoſe he doth <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 46.</note> cauſe the Truths of Rationality concerning himſelfe, firſt to become effectual upon the conſcience, before the underſtanding is obliged conſcionably to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain Revealed Truths. For he who is not capable of that meaſure of Faith which common Reaſon it ſelf doth beget upon the natural apprehenſions of God and his Truths written in the heart; how can he be thought ſuſceptible of the other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which dependeth onely upon Revelation and Divine Tradition? We conclude therefore, that theſe Precognitions are firſt to be handled as matters requiſite, to fit the mind of a natural man to receive that which is to follow after, becauſe I conceive, not that the Principles of the life of Godlineſſe which are to follow, are to be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as the products of theſe fore-going Truths; but onely as matters ſubſequent unto the ſame, in reſpect of the order of things to be taught. Theſe <hi>Praecognita,</hi> are <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupponenda,</hi> but not <hi>Principia,</hi> becauſe I take a Principle of Godlineſſe to be ſuch a Truth, from which a Concluſion of divine faith and love may flow: But that cannot flow from any truth which is entertained upon meer natural Grounds, as I ſuppoſe, without ſpiritual Revelation and Illumination: for divine Faith, as it is the gift of God, and not the product of humane Reaſoning; ſo it muſt needs have a higher Principle then theſe Precognitions, namely ſome truth, as revealed immediately by God unto the Conſcience to convince it, that he doth offer himſelfe unto it to be a Saviour. And this is the reaſon, why I would have the Precognitions, and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Godlineſſe diſtinguiſhed; namely, becauſe they are truths of a different na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; yet they are ſubordinate, but ſo, that the latter cannot follow the former, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome ſpeciall work of God upon the mind.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Concerning the Principles.</head>
                  <p>THe Principles of the life of Godlineſſe, are ſuch Truths as ſet the mind upon the apprehenſion of ſupernatural Objects, and beget thereby the acts of divine Faith therein, which worketh through love in the whole Man; all which is acceptable unto God.</p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:93868:11"/>
                  <p>Now all the Truths which beget divine Faith and Love, proceed from one Root, which is the Tenor of the Covenant, which God hath appointed to be offered from the Scriptures, by the Preaching of the Goſpel in his name, to be believed and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained by all: for all that God doth aime at in his dealing with Man-kind, next un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the manifeſtation of the glory of his goodneſſe over all his Creatures, is chiefly this, to ſhew himſelfe a Saviour, in uniting man by a Covenant <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 24. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 7.</note> of Grace unto himſelfe, that he being guided by his Counſel, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kept the faith therein, may afterward be received into glory.</p>
                  <p>The Covenant of Grace then is, the great and fundamental Principle of all the Principles of the life of Godlineſſe: for as there is none other way appointed to unite man unto God, and reſtore us again from our fall to integritie, but this way of a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant: ſo there is nothing which we can do acceptably towards God, or profitably for our own ſalvation; but that which is done in order to the Tenor thereof. Whence followeth alſo, that all our knowledge is not otherwiſe uſeful, nor to be ſought after upon any other ground, but as it leadeth to the obſervation of the Covenant; nor to be entertained for any other aime, but as it is ſubordinate unto the Tenor thereof: for as no man ever was, is, or can be ſaved, but he that is faithful in the Covenant of Grace with God; ſo no matter of knowledge can be ſaving to any man, but that which inableth him to keep the Tenor thereof. Hereunto then all truths, both Theoretical and Practical, are finally to be referred; and therefore in the Doctrine of the life of Godlineſſe, the Covenant muſt be made the ground of all the principles of Faith, from which the duties of obedience muſt flow: And I am fully perſwaded, both upon the grounds of found reaſon, which a natural morall man is capable of; and upon the grounds of divine Teſtimony and ſpiritual experience, that all doubtful matters in Divinity, whether they concern the points of Knowledge, or of Practice, may not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be reſolved by the right underſtanding of Gods aime towards us, and of our dutie towards him in the Covenant; but that the Reſolutions thereof (of what kind ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver) muſt be examined by, and applyed unto the Analogy of Faith concerning the Covenant, before ever they can bring true peace to the Conſcience of any man; and therefore my advice ſhall be unto thoſe who will undertake any part of this Work, that they keep alwayes the Covenant in their eye, as Marriners do the North point of the Compaſs, to ſteer their Courſe by it in all their Meditations; for it is mainly for want of this Directory, that both in our Notions and Actions concerning Religion, we run ſuch wild courſes: nor is it poſſible (as I conceive) ever to unite the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of Chriſtianity to each other, to heale their Breaches and Diviſions in Doctrine and Practice, and to make them live together as brethren in one Spirit ought to do, without the ſame ſenſe of the Covenant, by which they may be made to perceive the termes upon which God doth unite all thoſe that are his Children unto himſelfe, and upon which every one that is in Covenant with God, is bound in Conſcience, through love unto God, to maintain the unitie of the Spirit in the bond of peace with thoſe that are his Children, who all alike, and by the ſame very way, are in Covenant with him.</p>
                  <p>The knowledge of the Covenant then, being the fundamental Principle, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto all other Truths are to be reduced, that they may be received unto the end for which they are revealed, we ſhall endeavour to ſhew what the Doctrines of divine Faith are, which are ſubordinate thereunto; and which by vertue of that ſubordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are able to beget love towards God in a believing ſoul; for no doctrine of Faith doth otherwiſe oblige any man to love and obedience towards God, then as it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to manifeſt Gods love unto us, as he is become our Saviour, and to make us faithfull towards him in the Covenant.</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:93868:11"/>
                  <p>I conceive then, that all the Doctrines of divine Faith, tend either to the erecting and ſettling of the Covenant of Grace with us, or to the confirmation of our Faith in the truth thereof.</p>
                  <p>To Erect and ſettle the Covenant with us, we muſt needs know, 1. The true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of the Covenant wherein it is revealed. 2. The things belonging to the true Tenor thereof, as they are offered to us in that Inſtrument. 3. The Motives for which we ſhould embrace and entertaine the ſame: for if any of theſe three points be wanting, we cannot be ſound in the obſervation thereof.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the true Inſtrument of the Covenant, we believe the ſame to be the Canonical Scriptures; whereof two things muſt be known: Firſt, What the proper Character of Canonical Scripture is. Secondly, How the truth of God for the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Covenant, is therein offered unto us.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the firſt; this is to be believed,</p>
                  <p>That no Books are to be accounted Canonical Scripture, that is, the Word of God revealing his Covenant to Mankind; but ſuch as are written in the Hebrew Tongue, and were given to the Jewiſh Church to be a Rule of their profeſſion in order to the Covenant; or were written in the Greek tongue, and were given to the firſt Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſtianitie, as well Jews as Gentiles for the ſame end.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the ſecond; this is to be believed,</p>
                  <p>That theſe Books offer the Covenant unto our Conſideration, and all divine Truths belonging to the knowledge thereof, with infallible and uncontrolable authority, moſt perfectly and very clearly, to ſuch as have an upright deſire to know it.</p>
                  <p>And concerning theſe three Matters of Infallibility, Perfection and Evidence, which we believe to be in the Scripture, this is further more diſtinctly to be believed.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Concerning the infallibility of the Scripture, we believe that the truth of God revealed in the Canonical Scriptures, is ſo highly and incontrolably credible, that no man, no not an Apoſtle himſelf, nor an Angel from Heaven is to be believed, who ſhould contradict the ſame: but all Men, Churches, Councels, Fathers, Schools, and their Writings, Sayings, Actions, and Thoughts concerning divine Matters, are to be examined thereby, as by the onely rule of truth and righteouſneſſe, and if they agree not therewith, they are to be rejected.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Concerning, the perfection of the Canon we believe; That the Word of God revealed therein, is ſo compleat, both for the matter and manner of expreſſion, that neither any thing unprofitable is therein delivered; nor any thing profitable or needful to be known, therein omitted; but all things of Doctrine and Reproof, of Correction and Inſtruction in Righteouſneſs and for Comfort, whether to be believed or hoped for, or to be done or left undone unto ſalvation, are more then ſufficiently laid open, and preſcribed in a form of ſound words, which ought not to be altered; ſo that all heatheniſh Philoſophie in Divine matters, and all humane Traditions, and will-worſhip in the ſervice of God, are to be utterly rejected: nor is it lawful for any to conceive, that they can ſpeak of matters of Faith more exactly and properly, in reſpect of the things themſelves; or more conveniently and fitly, in reſpect of the Capacities of men, then the Holy Ghoſt hath done in thoſe Writings.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Concerning their clearneſs this is to be believed;</p>
                  <p>That the word of God revealed therein, is ſo evident and eaſie to be underſtood, that the meaneſt Capacitie of thoſe that are come to the years of diſcretion, if they be godly and deſirous to do Gods will, ſearching the Scriptures diligently may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out difficulty comprehend all things neceſſary to be known unto ſalvation; ſo that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93868:12"/> none ought, by reaſon of any ſuppoſed darkneſs to be therein, to abſtain from reading the Scriptures, which is a duty moſt ſutable and neceſſary to all.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the things belonging to the Tenour of the Covenant.</head>
                  <p>COncerning the Tenour of the Covenant, as it is revealed in the Canonical Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, three things muſt be opened.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Who the Parties are, which are concerned therein, and what their Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to one another.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, What the form of the contract is, according to which the Covenant is made with thoſe that are concerned therein.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, What the way is, by which it is eſtabliſhed amongſt men, that they may embrace it, and have the benefit thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the parties.</head>
                  <p>THe Parties concerned in the Covenant, are, God and Man, at a diſtance by reaſon of ſin; and Jeſus Chriſt the Mediator of God and man, who reconcileth them by his ſatisfaction and righteouſneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of God.</head>
                  <p>GOd is to be taken notice of, as he hath revealed himſelf in his Word, to be the Saviour, and our God by a Covenant; ſo that nothing is either neceſſary or profitable to be known of him further then what ſerves for this end; and to this effect, he hath revealed himſelf in his Being, in his Will, and in his Works.</p>
                  <p>His Being is revealed in the Properties of his nature, and the ſubſiſtence thereof which we call Perſonalitie.</p>
                  <p>The Properties of his Nature, are revealed to ſhew what he is, and who he is.</p>
                  <p>The Properties ſhewing what he is, <hi>That he is a Spirit living of himſelf,</hi> Joh. 4. 24. and 5. 26.</p>
                  <p>The Properties ſhewing who he is, are theſe,</p>
                  <p>That he is the onely true God alone; in Being infinite, eternal, incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, every where preſent, ſimple, unchangeable, all-knowing, all wiſe, all-free, all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, all-holy, all-mighty, all-happy, all-good, all-true, all-faithfull, and full of all mercy and compaſſion.</p>
                  <p>His ſubſiſtence is in three, who bear witneſs in Heaven: the Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one and the ſame God, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 7. The Father unbegotten; the Son onely begotten; and the Holy-Ghoſt proceeding from the Father and the Son.</p>
                  <p>His Will is revealed in the properties of his Counſels which are wiſe, good, free and eſtabliſhed for ever.</p>
                  <p>His Works are revealed in the Creation, Preſervation and Government of the World, and eſpecially of Mankinde therein, over whom he delighteth to exerciſe Loving kindneſs, Judgement and Righteouſneſs in the Earth, for his own <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. 24.</note> Glory, and according to the tenour of the Covenant.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of Man.</head>
                  <p>MAn is to be taken notice of as he is ſpoken of in the Word, to be of God, to belong unto God, and obliged to depend upon God by a Covenant in his Three-fold ſtate. 1. In the ſtate of Innocencie. 2. In the ſtate of Guilt and Miſery. 3. In the ſtate of Grace and Reconciliation unto God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:93868:12"/>
                  <head>Of the Mediator Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>JEſus Chriſt the Mediator of the new Covenant between God and Man, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in the Word to relate unto both. 1. In reſpect of his two-fold Nature in one perſon. 2. In reſpect of his threefold Office, of Prophet, Prieſt, and King, whereunto he was anointed. 3. In reſpect of the performance of all Duties belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thoſe Offices in his two-fold ſtate, the one of Humiliation by his life and death on earth, the other of exaltation by his power and glory in heaven.</p>
                  <p>In all which, as the fitneſs which is in Chriſts Perſon, Natures and offices, to work out redemption for us, and to ſettle the Covenant of Grace between God and us, is to be taken notice of, ſo the Work, Firſt of Reconciliation between God and us, as this was effected according to the purpoſe of God in the Covenant: Secondly, Of the Reſtitution of our nature to a ſtate of Union and Communion with God, as this doth enable us to obſerve the Covenant on our part: and Thirdly, Of Chriſts Mediation and Interceſſion in heaven for us, as he doth continue us in that ſtate of Grace which is the effect of the Covenant, is alſo to be acknowledged; that not onely the Relation which is between God and us in Chriſt, may be believed; but the Tenor of the Covenant, as it is offered to us in the Word by him, may be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the Form of the Contract.</head>
                  <p>IN the form of the contract, two Things muſt be acknowledged. 1. With whom the contract is made properly and directly, and with whom indirectly. 2. What the tearms of the agreement are, by which it is made with each of them.</p>
                  <p>The contract of the Covenant, is properly and directly made onely with Chriſt Jeſus; and indirectly with thoſe that believe in him, and make profeſſion of his name; for Chriſt is given as the Covenant of God unto them, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 42. 6. and 49. 8. and they are received only for his ſake, and not for any thing in themſelves.</p>
                  <p>The Termes of the Agreement by which the Covenant is made with Chriſt, are theſe: That whoſoever ſhall be redeemed by him, and be found in him, <hi>not having their own righteouſneſſe, but the righteouſneſſe of God</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſai.</hi> 59. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>through faith, to be made conformable unto the image of the Son of God, ſhall become Children of God, and Heirs of eternal glory,</hi> Rom. 3. 24. <hi>Juſtified freely by his Grace through the Redemption that is in Jeſus Christ,</hi> Phil. 3. 9. <hi>be found in him, &amp;c.</hi> Rom 8. 29. <hi>Predeſtinate to be conformed to the Image of his Son,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>per totum.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>that he might be the firſt born amongſt many Brethren,</hi> Joh. 1. 12. <hi>He gave them power to become the Sons of God; and</hi> Joh. 6. 39. <hi>I ſhould loſe nothing of all which he hath given me, but raiſe it up again at the laſt day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The terms of the Agreement by which the Covenant is made in Chriſt with the Believers, are; <hi>That God will be merciful to their unrighteouſneſſe, and remember their iniquities no more; that he will write his laws in their hearts, and put them in their minds: that he will be to them a God, and they ſhall be to him a People; and that they ſhall all be taught of God from the leaſt unto the greateſt.</hi> Heb. 8 10, 11, 12. The tearms of the agreement by which the Covenant is made in Chriſt, with thoſe that make profeſſion of his Name, are, <hi>That every one who nameth the name of Chriſt, ſhould depart from iniquitie,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 19. <hi>That ſuch as ſeparate themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e Lord, and touch not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> by him; that he will dwell amongſt them, and walk <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> they ſhall be his people: that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ll be a Father unto</hi>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:93868:13"/> 
                     <hi>them, and they ſhall be his Sons and Daughters,</hi> 2 Cor. 6. 16, 17, 18. <hi>And that every one who doth ſuffer with Chriſt, ſhall alſo reign with him,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 12. Rom. 8. 17.</p>
                  <p>Hitherto we have mentioned the heads of matters, which ſhew what the Tenor of the Covenant is: now follow thoſe things which ſhew the way, how amongſt men it is eſtabliſhed, that they may embrace it, and have the benefit of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the eſtabliſhment of the Contract with Men for Chriſts ſake.</head>
                  <p>THat this contract might be ratified and inalterably confirmed, to the benefit of Man-kind, Jeſus Chriſt died, and made theſe promiſes his Teſtament unto thoſe that believe and make profeſſion of his Name; and riſing again from the Dead by the power of his God head, he is gone into heaven to adminiſter from thence this Teſtament unto theſe unto whom he did bequeath it.</p>
                  <p>To this effect the Goſpel was preached, and is to be publiſhed unto the end of the World, by the gifts of the holy Ghoſt which Chriſt did ſend down, and will ſend down from heaven upon Men: for this is a part of the Covenant which the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath made with thoſe that are in Chriſt for his ſake, that his Spirit which is upon Chriſt, and his Words which he did put in his mouth, ſhall not depart out of his mouth, nor out of the mouth of his Seed, nor out of the mouth of his Seeds Seed, from henceforth and forever; <hi>Iſai.</hi> 59. 20. 21.</p>
                  <p>In this Adminiſtration of the Teſtament for the eſtabliſhment of the Covenant, two things are to be acknowledged.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What the general offer of Grace is on Gods part, calling all men to Chriſt to partake of the Covenant.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. How the particular Tearms of the contract are made good with Believers, and with the Profeſſors of Chriſts name.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the general offer of Grace.</head>
                  <p>IN the general Call of all Men unto Grace, three things are to be acknowledged. 1. What ſtate they are in who are called unto Chriſt. 2. What they are called unto in him. 3. By what way they come to him.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the firſt, we believe; That God hath appointed the Goſpel to be preached to Men dead in ſins and treſpaſſes, who have no abilitie of themſelves at all to will any thing which is ſpiritually good; far leſs to convert themſelves, or to prepare themſelves thereunto.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the ſecond, we believe; That they are called to receive the pardon of their ſins, reſt and eaſe to their ſouls, and the light of life, according to that of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the Apoſtles. <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour and are heavy-laden, and I will give you reſt,</hi> Mat. 11. 28. <hi>And be it known unto you, that through this Man is preached unto you forgiveneſſe of ſins; and by him all that believe are juſtified from all things, from which ye could not be juſtified by the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>Act.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3. 38. 39. <hi>And awake thou that ſleepeſt, and ariſe from the dead, and Chriſt ſhall give thee light,</hi> Ephe. 5. 14. <hi>And he that followeth me, ſhall not walk in darkneſſe, but ſhall have the light of life,</hi> Joh. 8. 12.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the third, we believe, that the way by which M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n come to <hi>Chriſt</hi> and follow him, is Repentance from dead Works, and Faith towards God, according to that of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles, <hi>The Kingdom of God is at hand: Repent ye, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93868:13"/> the Gospel,</hi> Mar. 1. 15. <hi>Teſtifying both to the Jews, and alſo to the Greeks, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance towards God, and faith towards our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Act. 20. 21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How the particular Tearms of the Covenant are made good to Believers.</head>
                  <p>IN the Particular Call of Believers, three things ſhould be acknowledged. 1. How they are made to believe and entertain the offer of the Covenant. 2. How God doth make good the Tenour of his Covenant in Chriſt towards them. 3. How they are made ſenſible of their happy condition in Grace, to apprehend their right to Glory.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the firſt, we believe, that ſuch as hear the Word, and are moved to anſwer the Call given them therein, and to embrace effectually the Promiſes of the Covenant through the knowledge of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, are moved and enabled ſo to do by a free and ſpecial grace of God conferred upon them, who of his own good pleaſure doth work in them by the gift of Faith, both to will their converſion, and to perform the ſame, ſo that they are brought Free-willingly unto Chriſt, and deſire above all things to be found in him to partake of the merits of his death.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the Second. We believe that God doth make good unto all ſuch as by Faith are found in Chriſt, the Tenour of his Covenant, when by his grace they are juſtified and adopted to be his children, and ſanctified by the Spirit of regeneration, whereby they are alſo ſealed unto the day of their final Redemption, and enabled to walk and perſevere in the obedience of Faith and in the enjoyment of grace unto the end.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the Third, We believe that all true Believers may have a comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able aſſurance of their bleſſed eſtate in grace, by the teſtimony of the Spirit of Adoption unto their conſcience, given them in the ſincerity of their walking with God in the Covenant, according to that which the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 15, 16. <hi>The Spirit of adoption whereby we cry Abba Father, the Spirit it ſelf beareth witneſs with our ſpirit that we are the Children of God:</hi> and a <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 12. <hi>Our rejoycing is this: the teſtimony of our conſcience, that in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity by the grace of God we have had our converſation in the World.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How the Particular Tearms of the Covenant are made good to Profeſſors.</head>
                  <p>IN the particular Call of Profeſſors to entertain profeſſedly the duties, and therein to receive the Graces of the Covenant, Two things are to be acknowledged, wherein the Communion of Saints do conſiſt.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, That ſuch as profeſſe the name of Jeſus Chriſt are to be gathered together, and bound to joyn themſelves in one body as members one of another in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, That they are to be perfected and built up by the work of the Miniſtry, towards the effect of the Covenant.</p>
                  <p>Concerning The gathering of Profeſſors together into one Body.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, We believe that to effect this, the Lord hath given gifts unto men; At firſt Apoſtles, Prophets and Evangeliſts, to lay the foundation of his Church, and now Paſtors and Teachers to build thereupon, who have continued and ſhall continue by a lawfull Ordinary Calling unto the End of the World.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, We believe alſo that the gathering together of Profeſſors into one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, is lawfully performed, when they profeſſedly give up themſelves unto God through the Miniſtry of the Teſtament which Chriſt hath inſtituted, and by their profeſſed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93868:14"/> ſubjecting of themſelves to all the Ordinances of Gods houſe, which make the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers as one in the Covenant with God, ſo one with each other before the World in the profeſſion thereof to Gods glory.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the perfecting and building up of the Profeſſors as one man, till they come to the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt in the Covenant. We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the Lord hath appointed ſeverall adminiſtrations of the gifts of his Spirit to be uſed amongſt them in the houſehold of Faith, ſome relating principally to the inward man, and ſome to the outward man: and all to be performed as the ſervices of Love in the communion of Saints.</p>
                  <p>The adminiſtration of gifts relating principally to the inward man, is in the duties of publick worſhip, whereunto Profeſſors are obliged to apply themſelves by attending to the word of Propheſie, and by joyning in the ordinary Sacrifices of Prayers and Praiſes to be offered up unto God in his houſe, and in the extraordinary and lawfull uſe of an Oath and of a Lot, wherein Gods preſence is to be atteſted and petitioned, when neceſſary matters cannot otherwiſe be determined.</p>
                  <p>The adminiſtration of gifts relating principally to the outward man, is in the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Love belonging to the communion of Saints, wherein Profeſſors are obliged to watch over one another, obſerving each others converſation, and to ſupply each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wants in all things. And although in ſome reſpect, all are bound alike to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter their gifts to each other by themſelves, yet We believe that the Elderſhip is more eſpecially bound to over-ſee the wayes of their Flocks, and to make uſe of the Keyes of the kingdom of heaven towards them, to open and ſhut the dore of comfort unto them as they ſhall find cauſe: and that the Deaconſhip is more particularly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to conſider the bodily neceſſities of the Saints, and to diſtribute the Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Profeſſors to ſuch as ſtand in need thereof.</p>
                  <p>Hitherto, We have ſpoken of the wayes by which the Covenant is eſtabliſhed: that is to ſay, whereby God doth offer it, the Elect do embrace it, and the Profeſſors do entertain it before the World. Now followeth the Reaſon wherefore all men are bound thus to entertain it and keep it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the Third.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Wherefore all men are bound to entertain the Offer, and keep the Tenor of the Covenant.</head>
                  <p>THe Ground and Motive wherefore all men ſhould receive the Offer, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Tenor of the Covenant which God doth make with them, is Two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, becauſe God hath now commanded all men every-where to Repent, and believe the Goſpel. <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 30. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24. 57.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, becauſe God hath appointed a Day wherein the Dead ſhall be raiſed, and the World judged in righteouſneſs by the man Jeſus Chriſt <hi>(Acts</hi> 17. 31.) who will receive none into Glory, but ſuch as have kept his Covenant by Repentance and Faith, and by making profeſſion thereof before the World.</p>
                  <p>Hitherto, We have mentioned the fundamental Heads of Faith which concern the Revealing and the eſtabliſhing of the Covenant. Now followeth that which concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the confirmation of the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Matters of Truth to be known to confirm us in the Covenant.</head>
                  <p>COncerning the confirmation of the Covenant, two things are to be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:93868:14"/>
                  <p>Firſt, What God on his part doth offer to aſſure us of the truth of his meaning and the Reality of his purpoſe in the Covenant.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, What the Believers on their part are bound to do in accepting that which God doth offer for their confirmation in the promiſes of the Covenant.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the Firſt, We believe,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, That God hath given unto ſuch as he hath received into his Covenant, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Signs to repreſent the Reality of his Purpoſe, to confirm the things promiſed in the Word, and to conveigh the aſſurance thereof unto them thereby, as badges of his ſpecial Love to them in the Profeſſion.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, We believe further, That theſe Signes are appointed for three ſeveral uſes in the houſe of God:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, for the Reception of Profeſſors into Gods houſe, to oblige them to entertain the Covenant profeſſedly; and to this effect, Baptiſm is appointed.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, for the maintenance and continuance of Profeſſors in the unity of the Covenant with God, and one with another; to which End the Lords Supper is inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted: and</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, for the ſettlement of orderly Courſes and the due obſervation and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of all Gods Ordinances in the houſe wherewith he is in Covenant: and for this uſe the Impoſition of the hands of the Presbyterie is appointed; <hi>viz.</hi> to give lawful authority to thoſe that are Publick perſons in the Profeſſion of the Covenant.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the Second, We believe;</p>
                  <p>Firſt, That the Faithfull are bound to make uſe of theſe Signes for the Ends for which God hath given them, by taking them up and applying them to thoſe to whom he hath ordained them, as Evidences of their dependance upon him, and of their owning of his Covenant, and of their Profeſſion thereof before the World.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, We believe that the Sign of Baptiſm is to be applyed unto all whom God hath received into his Covenant, and belong unto his houſhold; that the Sign of the Lords Supper is to be applyed unto all that have embraced, and do enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain profeſſedly the Covenant; And that the Sign of the Impoſition of hands is to be applyed unto all that are called and to be ſet apart for any Publick Office in the Church.</p>
                  <p>Hitherto We have reckoned up the Heads of the Principles of the life of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as they riſe from and relate to the Covenant, which is the ground of all Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Relations between God and Us. Now followeth that which is to be known con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſubſtance of that life which God doth work in Us by the Covenant.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Concerning the Subſtantials of the Life of Godlineſs.</head>
                  <p>THe Subſtantials of the life of Godlineſs are nothing elſe but the power &amp; practice of that ſtate and life whereby we are made one with God; and walking with Chriſt in the Covenant, we enjoy God in him both outwardly and inwardly.</p>
                  <p>The enjoyment of God in the Inward man, is by the New creature and his life of communion with God.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the New creature theſe things ſhould be known;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What that change is whereby a man becometh from an Old, a New creature, and is born again.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. How that change is wrought in the Soul by the knowledge of Chriſt in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; and how the conſcience is quickned therein by him, and raiſed to a new life.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. How that change is diſcerned to be real and ſincere; and the deceitfulneſs of a pretended or imaginary change diſcovered.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:93868:15"/>
                  <p>Concerning the Life of inward communion with God, theſe things ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What it is to know and worſhip God in Spirit and truth.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. How the Spiritual man doth walk with God by faith, by hope, by love, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Covenant.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What that vertue is, whereby he is enabled to have God alwayes before his eyes, and to do all things in the name of Jeſus Chriſt, giving glory to God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through him.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. What Tentations are oppoſite unto this Life, both from the corruption of our nature, and from Satan; and how they are reſiſted.</p>
                  <p>The enjoyment of God in the Outward man, is by the open profeſſion and practice of Obedience unto the will and wayes of God in all things: which hath two chief parts.</p>
                  <p>The firſt is, To deny the practice and profeſſion of ungodlineſs, and of all worldly Luſts. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 11, 12.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond is, To offer up our bodies as a living ſacrifice unto God, by our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſerving of him in the Covenant. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 1.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the denying of ungodlineſs and worldly Luſts, theſe things ſhould be known.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What the Practice and Profeſſion of Impiety is; as it proceedeth</p>
                  <p>Firſt, from Natural Atheiſm.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, from vain Philoſophy, the Traditions of men, and the Rudiments of the World.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, from the ſtrong Deluſions and the deceitfullneſs of unrighteouſneſs, which Satan is permitted to make uſe of in the end of the World.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. How the Conſciences of Natural men are to be dealt withal and convicted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the wickedneſs of their Practices in this kind.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What the nature and the original is of Actual ſins, and how they proceed from the power of inbred Luſt.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. How the motions of Actual ſins are to be reſiſted; not only by the inward pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification of the heart, but alſo by the outward exerciſes of a Mortified life, wherein the body is kept under and brought into ſubjection. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 27.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the offering our bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ies a living Sacrifice unto God by the Covenant. Three things muſt be known, for the ordering of our converſation aright in reſpect of our ſelves, in reſpect of our Neighbour, and in reſpect of God: for hereunto the Apoſtle, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 12. doth referre all mens vertuous actions in this World, by Sobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Juſtice, and Religiouſneſs.</p>
                  <p>Sobriety doth comprehend all the way of our converſation with our ſelves; Juſtice all our converſation with our Neighbour; and Religiouſnes all our converſation to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God.</p>
                  <p>And theſe Heads of our outward converſation ought to be handled and taken up in this order; becauſe the duties of the Firſt kind are ſuch a ground-work for the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and Third, that without Sobriety in reſpect of our ſelves, nothing can be done rightly towards God or Man; And the Duties of the Second kind are in Gods own e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem preferred to the Duties of the Third; becauſe he doth require Mercy of us, and not Sacrifice; that is, the Works of Juſtice and <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 23. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 7, 8. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 11. to 19.</note> Charity towards our Neighbour, more then the Works of outward Worſhip towards himſelf.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:93868:15"/>
                  <head>Of the Ordering our way toward our ſelves by Sobriety.</head>
                  <p>TO be able to order our ſelves and all our wayes in Sobriety, we muſt know;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What the nature of Sobriety is, as it is a Rule of reſtraint to moderate our ſelves in all our Undertakings as they are ours.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. What the nature of our Intemperance and inclination to Exceſs is, and whence it cometh; <hi>viz.</hi> from Self-love; where we muſt know what Self-love and ſelf plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing is, and how all manner of Exceſs proceedeth from thence.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. How Sobriety doth proceed from the Grace of Self-denial, accompanied with Contentation, Meekneſs, and Lowlineſs, which Chriſt upon the Ground of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and Promiſe of Reſt doth invite us to learn of himſelf, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 29.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. What the proper work of Sobriety is, in reference to the natural acts of Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; where is to be noted that our natural affections may be two wayes vitious; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as they diſcompoſe and wrong us within our-ſelves, or as they tend to diſcompoſe and wrong our Neighbour. In the firſt Reſpect, they are to be regulated by Sobriety; in the ſecond by Juſtice: ſo that the proper work of Sobriety will be to keep the acts of our natural Affections within the bounds of that lawful and neceſſary uſe whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God hath appointed them. And to diſcover theſe bounds, the natural Deſires and Actions of Chriſt in the fleſh as he did ſubordinate them unto the life of God in the Spirit, according to the Covenant, are to be taken notice of as a Rule.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. What the Rules of Sobriety are in particular, in reſpect of the luſts of the fleſh, as meat and drink, eaſe and ſoftneſs, the conjugal bed, and all other delightful actions inherent to the body.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. What the Rules of Sobriety are in reſpect of the luſts of the eye, as outward ſights for pleaſure and curioſity, the covetouſneſs of Riches, and whatſoever elſe may be a purchaſe, or from without an Object of the eye to luſt after.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. What the Rules of Sobriety are in reſpect of the pride of life, as the affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Glory and Honour, the vanity of Worldly Pomp and appearance; the flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery of our-ſelves in the way of our Paſſions, Emulation, Anger, Strife, Envy, and ſuch like, which are the fruits or companions of Pride.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. What the rules of Sobriety are for the ordering of our behaviour as well in ſpeeches as in actions, as at all times, ſo eſpecially in times of c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>s and adverſities, or of proſperity and joy, wherein there may be a provocation to exceed, and misbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have our ſelves in geſtures, if not in ſpeeches and actions contrary to Sobriety.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the Ordering of our way towards our Neighbours by Juſtice.</head>
                  <p>TO be able to order our way juſtly towards our Neighbour, we muſt know, 1. What the nature of Juſtice is in reference to a Society, as it is a Rule to direct every one to pay that which they owe to one another in their Society.</p>
                  <p>2. What the nature of Injuſtice is, and what doth incline men to deprive others of that which is their due; namely the ſpirit of men which luſteth to envy. Here then we ſhould know what envy is, and how the ſpirit thereof ſupported with Pride and covetouſneſs doth ſet men upon all manner of Injuſtice.</p>
                  <p>3. How the Acts and way of Juſtice proceed from the grace of brotherly love, and eſpecially from theſe Fundamental Rules thereof; <hi>As ye would that men ſhould do to you, do ye alſo to them likewiſe,</hi> Luke 6. 31. And, <hi>Ye have been call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d</hi> (viz. by God in the Covenant) <hi>unto Liberty: onely uſe not Liberty for an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the fleſh, but by love ſerve one another. Let every one pleaſe his</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 13. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>Neighbour for his good to edification as Chriſt pleaſed not himſelf, but</hi>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:93868:16"/> 
                     <hi>came to ſerve us for our good.</hi> Rom. 15. 2, 3, 7. Phil. 2. 3. till 9. <hi>Love one another as I loved you.</hi> Joh. 13. 34.</p>
                  <p>4. What the proper work of Juſtice is, in reference to that which is good, and by Love due unto others: namely to obſerve all inoffenſiveneſs and communicativeneſs towards every one.</p>
                  <p>5. What inoffenſiveneſs is, and by what Rules our wayes may be made void of offence: and of what importance the obſervation of thoſe Rules are to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the Covenant of Divine Love in Chriſt, whether their wayes relate to thoſe that are within, or without the Church.</p>
                  <p>6. What communicativeneſs is, and by what Rules all good things are to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted unto others, either as they ſtand in need thereof, or otherwiſe they may be profitable unto them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whether it be the Communication of Mercifulneſs by which we relieve them of their Miſeries; or of Bountifulneſs, by which we provoke them to Love and good Works.</p>
                  <p>7. How all Dutiful actions which we owe to others in word or deed concerning their perſons, or that which doth belong unto them, ought duely and obligeingly to be performed, that juſt things may be done juſtly.</p>
                  <p>8. What Rules of Juſtice are to be obſerved concerning the offices of Love com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively due to Enemies, to perſons indifferently affected, and to Friends in ſeveral degrees of neerneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the Ordering of our way towards God by Religiouſneſs.</head>
                  <p>TO be able to order our way toward God Religiouſly, we muſt know,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, What Religiouſneſs is, or what the nature of that tie and obligation is, by which thoſe that are in Covenant with God are bound in all their outward carriages to ſhew that they depend upon him and regard him.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, What doth incline us naturally to Irreligiouſneſs, that is, not to referre our ſelves unto God, nor reſpect him as we are bound to do by the tenour of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, in all our wayes; and whether it be not this that we eaſily forget his Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſence, and the Supremacy of his Influence over all Creatures, and regard too at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentively the properties of Secondary Cauſes as they may have, and the thoughts of men as they have an Influence upon us.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, how this obligation doth proceed from the conſcionable apprehenſion of theſe following, and ſuch like laws and Rules of Juſtice and Equity.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. You are bought with a price; Glorifie therefore the Lord in your Soul and in your Body, which are the Lords. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 2.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He that is aſhamed of me and of my words in this adulterous and ſinful genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Son of man ſhall be aſhamed of him, when he cometh into the Glory of his Father with the holy Angels. <hi>Mar.</hi> 8. 38. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 32, 33. <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 8, 9.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We ſhould walk worthy of God who hath called us to his glory and kingdom. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 12.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. As Children of God in the World without blame, we ſhould ſhine as Lights, and hold forth the Word of life. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 15, 16. and ſuch like in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 15, 16, 17, 18. and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2, 8. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 9. 10, 11, 12. and 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 2, 3. and elſewhere.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, What the proper work of Religiouſneſs is and whether it be not to walk alwayes in the light of a good conſcience towards God and men, <hi>Acts</hi> 23. 1. and 24 16.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, Whether the proper Rule of a good conſcience in this walking, is not to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93868:16"/> follow the grace of God which bringeth Salvation, in ſincerity, and not according to worldly wiſdom, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 12. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2, 11, 12. And whether the parts of this walking are not chiefly or ſummarily theſe; 1. To confeſſe and profeſs openly the truth. 2. To worſhip God privately and publickly, obſerving all his Ordinances.</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, What the Rules are of a Religious open confeſſion of the truth by word of mouth.</p>
                  <p>Seventhly, What the Rules are of a Religious profeſſion of the truth in deed and converſation.</p>
                  <p>Eighthly, What the Rules are of a Religious ſuffering for the confeſſion and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the truth.</p>
                  <p>Ninthly, What the Rules are of a Religious worſhipping of God in private, by Prayer, by Reading and Meditating the Word, and by private conference.</p>
                  <p>Tenthly, What the Rules are of a Religious worſhipping of God in publick, by Hearing the word, and Joyning with the Profeſſors of the name of Chriſt in Prayer and praiſes, and in the fellowſhip of all the publick Ordinances, whereby the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is eſtabliſhed or confirmed amongſt men.</p>
                  <p>HItherto we have mentioned the Subſtantials of the life of Godlineſs in reſpect of the diſtinct parts thereof as well inward as outward:</p>
                  <p>But becauſe a Thing is neither in it ſelf compleat, which hath not all the parts joyned in ſuch a way as is ſutable to the proper End thereof, nor in reſpect of us compleatly known, except we underſtand both what the property of each part is diſtinctly; and alſo what the joynt frame of all is, which makes up that whole, which is the Reſult of their union: therefore unto the former conſideration another muſt be added, wherein the union of all theſe parts is to be diſcovered, that we may ſee the entire frame of the whole courſe which is conformable unto the will of God in all things, as well inwardly as outwardly, in all Duties at once which will make up the ſubſtance of the parts of a Godly life.</p>
                  <p>And to bring us unto this Perfection, God hath given a peculiar Rule whereunto he doth oblige all men to be ſo fully conformable, that whoſoever tranſgreſſeth in any one Point thereof, is guilty of all, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. 10. becauſe the true and perfect ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of any one Duty, doth import a full confirmity of our Wills to the Will of him who doth command all the reſt; and the tranſgreſſion of Gods will in any one particular, doth bewray an inconformity of our wills from the will of him who doth command all the reſt; and this is to be a tranſgreſſor of the whole Law; becauſe the whole Law is nothing elſe but the will of God; and the ſubſtance of the whole Obedience is nothing elſe but a total ſubjection of our wills unto his will, as it is revealed in the Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2 20. for God hath given the form of knowledge and of the truth in the Law, to this end that we ſhould not diſpleaſe him, but to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udy to pleaſe him in all things; for the whole ſubſtance of our Religious fear and love is con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto this aim, that we ſhould do nothing that is diſpleaſing, but every thing as it is acceptable unto him. Our performance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of all Duties in order to the fulfilling of Gods will, and obſervance of the Law, is the ſubſtance of the whole life of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. For the Ten Commandments given in Mount Sinai, which God wrote <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in Tables of St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne, are the Univerſal Rule of Righteouſneſs, as they contain the nature of all Duties which are generally obliging unto every one, and as they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend in one expreſſion, both the Spiritual and Bodily perfection of every Humane Action.</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:93868:17"/>
                  <p>The Doctrine then of the Ten Commandments ſhould be delivered to this effect, in Four diſtinct Heads.</p>
                  <p>The Firſt ſhould contain the Rules of interpreting the Commandments.</p>
                  <p>The Second ſhould let us ſee the Abſtract of all the Duties commanded, and ſins forbidden therein.</p>
                  <p>The Third ſhould let us know the Definition or Deſcription of all theſe Duties and Sins, with the Means and Helps ſubordinate unto the duties, and the cauſes which beget, and the ſignes which manifeſt the ſins; and although perhaps ſome of the things formerly mentioned in ſome of the parts of the life of godlineſs, may come to be named here again, yet this is not to be counted any Tautologie or ſuperfluity, becauſe the ſame thing may be more then once handled, under different notions and reſpects in ſeverall places; Here then all duties whatſoever, and every thing oppoſite thereunto, are only to be handled, as they are commanded and forbidden in the Law, which is the univerſall rule of Righteouſneſs, to ſhew the perfection of the Law, and the nature of every action, as it agreeth or diſagreeth with the rule, and the quality of every vertue and vice, as it is ranked by God in the whole frame of that life which the Law doth require or condemn: all which are material points of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and can no where be properly handled but in this conſideration of the Law.</p>
                  <p>The fourth and laſt head, ſhould deſcribe the watch which all men ſhould have, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well over themſelves, as over others for the obſervation of the Law; for as all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular vertues make up but one perfection of obedience, by their conformity, unto the Rule of the Law; ſo all mens obſervation of the Law in their ſeveral wayes, doth make up but one ſubmiſſion to the will of God in them all, their joynt care of each others conformity unto the Law; for all Profeſſors as they are members of each other in Chriſt, make up but one body and ſpiritual man in him; and this is the ſubſtance of the whole life of godlineſs, when by the grace and truth which is in Jeſus Chriſt, the righteouſneſs of the Law is fulfilled in us, who walk not after the fleſh, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſpirit; for the Law of the ſpirit of life, which is in Chriſt, being through Faith effectuall in us, to free us from the Law of ſin and death, which is in our nature, doth make us conformable unto all that is well-pleaſing unto God, ſo that in every thing we are enabled to prove what is that holy, perfect, and acceptable will of God.</p>
                  <p>Which things being laid open, I ſuppoſe all that juſtly may be deſired concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſubſtantials of the life of godlineſs, in the whole and parts, will be ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcovered; and ſo the ſecond part of this body of Practical Divinity will be made up.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the Circumſtantials of the Life of Godlineſſe.</head>
                  <p>ALthough the former rules of Piety, which are common to all Believers and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, may well ſuffice to direct every one upon all occaſions what to do, not only becauſe they contain the grounds of all duties, and the properties of all vertues; but becauſe God in the Covenant hath expreſly promiſed, that he himſelf will teach all his children; and Chriſt hath engaged himſelf to ſend unto his Diſciples, a ſpirit which ſhall lead them in all truth: yet ſeeing the Scripture doth lay open, not only the ſubſtantiall rules of the whole Profeſſion, in the general nature of vertue and vice by the precepts of the Law, but doth mention in particular tearms, the circumſtantial duties alſo which are conſiderable in order to the Profeſſion; therefore theſe ought diſtinctly to be opened, and made the third part of this body.</p>
                  <p>Where again I ſhall deſire that it may be obſerved, that the things here to be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93868:17"/> handled, ſhould be diſtinguiſhed from the ſame things handled before, in this reſpect that in the foregoing part, all actions are to be conſidered in order to that which is their perpetuall nature, and ſubſtantial property never to be altered; but in this part, all actions are to conſidered in order to that which is alterable in them according to the circumſtances; therefore in the former part, although the heads of all things which are to be mentioned here, may be brought in and named in their own places, yet the handling of them ought not to go any further, then to define the univerſal nature and properties thereof, as it is common to all times, places, caſes, and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; but in this part the particular caſes and circumſtances, which are ordinarily incident to perſons of ſeveral conditions, are to be taken into conſideration, to ſhew them the rule of their walking therein, to obſerve that which is righteous and anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the Law: Here then we preſuppoſe the knowledge of the definition, and true notion of all vertues and vices (which is the proper work of the ſubſtantial Doctrine, for under that reſpect all things are handled there) and we reflect upon the various ſubjects, objects, relations, and occaſions of putting forth theſe actions which are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to be vertuous or vicious, that the way of maintaining our courſe in vertue, and declining vice, may be known in matters circumſtantiall, aſwell as ſubſtantiall.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Circumſtantiall duties are of three ſorts, ſome regulate the naturall, ſome the ſpirituall circumſtances of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the Profeſſors, ſome relate unto both.</p>
                  <p>The naturall circumſtances concern either the Sex in reſpect of the difference which God hath made therein; or the ſocieties which ariſe amongſt men from the conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions thereof.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the difference which God hath put between the Male and the Female, we ſhould know this.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What the preheminency of the Male is above the Female, in reſpect of right, to mannage domeſtick and publick concernments.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. What the proper worke of each Sex is, which we may call the naturall calling thereof; that is, what the imployment is whereunto God hath created each Sex, that they ſhould advance his glory in their ſeverall kinds.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What the rules are, by which each Sex ſhould order it ſelfe, within thoſe bounds and limits of employment whereunto God hath appointed it.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the naturall Societies which ariſe amongſt men from their conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we obſerve that</p>
                  <p>The firſt natural Conjunction and Societie is of the Male and Female, of one with one, for the propagation of Mankind, which is Matrimonial, of which we ſhould know,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, What Gods appointment is concerning marriage; in reſpect</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Of the ends for which it is to be intended lawfully, and for which it ought not to be intended.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Of the perſons who may or may not joyn together in that ſtate.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Of the manner how it ought to be ſetled between theſe who may lawfully joyn therein.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Of the duties which married perſons owe to one another, by which they may obtaine the lawfull ends of their Conjunction, by Gods bleſſing.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Of the cauſes for which marriage may lawfully be diſſolved.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Of the manner and way how it ought to be, when needs it muſt be diſſolved.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, What the inclinations of men are to abuſe marriage, and what corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are become cuſtomary therein, even amongſt Profeſſors.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, How prejudiciall the abuſe of the ordinance of marriage is, not onely to the holy Profeſſion, but even to the Society of Mankinde.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:93868:18"/>
                  <p>Fourthly, How far both Miniſters and Magiſtrates are bound to endeavour each in their own way, to rectifie the abuſes of this Ordinance, by repreſſing all Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, Adultery, Inceſts, and other unlawfull Conjunctions, as Concubinate and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygamy, and whatſoever in this kinde is contrary to the will of God, and to the right uſe of nature.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond naturall Conjunction and Society is of Parents and Children, where we muſt know;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What the duty is of Parents towards their Children joyntly; in reſpect of their education, and of their ſettlement in a courſe of life in the world.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. What the duty of the Mother is towards the child whiles it is an Infant; how far ſhe is obliged to give it ſuck and attend it her ſelfe, and in what caſes ſhe may be diſpenſed withall in reference to theſe duties.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What the duty of the Father is toward the Childe after it is paſt the ſtate of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, and how far he is obliged to look to the education thereof himſelfe; and in what caſes he may be diſpenſed withall to commit it unto a Deputy.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. How the peculiar care of the Daughters belongeth to the Mother, and the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar care of the Sons to the Father, chiefly, when they are paſt childe-hood.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. What the duty of Children when they come to years of diſcretion is towards their Parents, and how they ought to yield unto them not onely honour and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but a requitall in their old age.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. How far the law of Marriage, by which a man is appointed to leave Father and Mother, and cleave to his wife, doth emancipate him from ſubjection and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency upon his Parents.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. How family duties ought to be obſerved in the Societies of Parents and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; and what obligation doth lie upon Parents to worſhip God with thoſe of their family.</p>
                  <p>The third naturall Conjunction and Society is of brethren and ſiſters, and of kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folks, where we muſt know;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What the nature and extent of the relation is, and how it differs from the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going of Man and Wife, and parent and childe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. What the duties of kinsfolks are towards each other.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What the proper care and affection is, which is more due unto kinsfolks re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, then unto others; though theſe in all reſpects be as commendable, and perhaps farre more commendable for grace and vertue then they.</p>
                  <p>The fourth naturall Conjunction and Society, is of Alliance, where we muſt know;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What the nature and extent of this relation is, and how far it is inferior unto that of kindred.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. What the proper duties thereof are more to each other, then to meer ſtrangers.</p>
                  <p>All theſe Conjunctions and Societies are properly naturall, and unavoydably ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, if we ſuppoſe the propagation of Mankinde by Marriage; there are other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions and ſocieties which are more voluntary and freely taken up, or left off, as there is cauſe ſound; and theſe are againe either of one with one, or of many toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a Society.</p>
                  <p>The voluntary conjunction and ſociety of one with one, is of Maſter and ſervant, where muſt be known;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For what ends, and in what employments, men ought to ſeek for others to ſerve them; and in what things they ought to ſerve themſelves.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. What the duties are of Maſters towards their Servants.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What lawfull ſervices and employments are in humane Societies, and for what
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93868:18"/> ends men ought to offer themſelves to be ſervants unto others.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. What the duties are which ſervants owe unto their Maſters, and how they ought as Chriſtians to performe the ſame.</p>
                  <p>The Voluntary Conjunction and Society of many together in one Body, is either of many Families to make a City, or of Cities to make Provinces, or of Provinces to make Nations and Kingdoms: all which are ſetled in their Relations by Laws, and maintained therein by Officers indued with Authority and Power to adminiſter the ſame; whence doth ariſe the Office of Magiſtrates and Subjects: where we muſt know,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Concerning Magiſtrates;</head>
                  <p n="1">1. VVHat a Magiſtrate is in the Societies of Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whence Magiſtrates have their Authority.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What the proper work of their Employment is for the good of the Publick Society; And whether it be not to procure the obſervation of Both the Tables of the Moſaical Law in the Common-wealth over which they are Rulers.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. How the Sword is committed unto them, and to be uſed by them for Vengeance againſt evill Doers, and for the Reward of thoſe that are good.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. For what End Taxes and Cuſtomes are to be laid upon Subjects.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. What Offices are neceſſary and lawfull to be conſtituted for the Peace and Safety of Humane Societies.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. What maketh Warre lawfull in a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, and what unlawfull.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. What Power he hath to adminiſter Oaths, and for what Ends.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Concerning Subjects we muſt know;</head>
                  <p n="1">1. VVHat the Duty of a Chriſtian Subject is towards the Supream and Subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Magiſtrates.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. How they ought to be ſubject not only for wrath, but for Conſcience ſake.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Wherein a Chriſtian ought not to be in ſubjection, or a Servant unto men.</p>
                  <p>HItherto we have mentioned the Heads of Matters which relate unto the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of the Natural life; now follow the Circumſtances of the Spiritual Life of Profeſſors.</p>
                  <p>THe Spiritual Life of Profeſſors doth Relate to the Church, either as it is made up of Members to make one Body; or as in it are Offices and Officers with ſeveral Charges.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Concerning the Members of the Church, we muſt know;</head>
                  <p n="1">1. VVHat Right and Relation a true Profeſſor of Chriſtianitie hath to any, or all the Churches of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. What uſe he ought to make of that Right and Relation; and how he ſhould apply himſelf to ſome particular Congregation, where his conveniency of Edification is greateſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. How the Common Profeſſion and the Duties of holy Communion with all the Members of Chriſt are to be maintained notwithſtanding the application may be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily made unto one particular Congregation.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. What the Care is which Members owe to one another in the Communion of Saints, to build up each other in the Common Profeſſion.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:93868:19"/>5. What the peculiar Duty and Reſpect is which all Profeſſors owe unto thoſe that are the Leaders of others in the Profeſſion, for their works ſake.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. How all Members and Profeſſors ought to walk towards thoſe that are without, as to adorn the Doctrine of the Goſpel in all things.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Concerning thoſe that bear Office in the Church of God We, must know;</head>
                  <p n="1">1. VVHat the Office of a Paſtor is, and how he ought to diſcharge it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. What the Office of the Teacher is, and how he ought to diſcharge it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. How the Duties of the Paſtor and Teacher are conjoynt, and how diſtinct and ſeparate.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. What the Office of a Ruling Elder is, and how he ought to diſcharge it.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. What the Office of a Deacon is, and how he ought to diſcharge it.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. What Correſpondence and Communion theſe Officers ought to have one with another, for the ſtrengthening of each others hands in their Duties towards the Flock.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. What Correſpondence and Communion the Officers of ſeveral Congregations ought to have one with another, for the maintaining of the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace amongſt themſelves, to prevent or remedy Differences, and for the propagating of the truth unto others that have not as yet received it.</p>
                  <p>Of all theſe ſtates and Relations, the Duties ſhould be laid open as they are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the Word diſtinctly.</p>
                  <p>Then the ſtate and Calling which hath a reſpect to all ſorts of Societies joyntly, as being the Seed-plot and Seminary of all Vertues to be exerciſed therein, is the ſtate of Schooles: where ought to be delivered;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What kinds of Schools ought to be conſtituted, ſutable to the Principles and Life of Chriſtianity.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To whom the Care of erecting and reforming of Schools doth belong: and what neceſſity there is of this work.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What the peculiar Duties are of School-Maſters and Miſtreſſes, and of Schollars of both Sexes.</p>
                  <p>Hitherto, I have reckoned up ſummarily the Heads of thoſe Truths which will make a full Body of Practical Divinity, if they be throughly handled, and if the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars which may be referred thereunto be fitly brought in.</p>
                  <p>As concerning the Supplement of Caſes of Conſcience, I ſhall ſay nothing for the preſent: hoping that if the Poſitive Truths be Compleatly handled, and a General Rule ſhewed how to draw from the Tenor of the Covenant, a reſolution of Conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Difficulties, there will be no great need of any large Treatiſe in this kind. Yet I will not deny but that a full Body of Caſe-Divinity may be uſefull, if well orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and publiſhed by it ſelf: but I would not have the Body of Poſitive Truths over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burdened with Caſes: becauſe our main Study ought to be about the knowledge of the Rules, and our exerciſe about the application of the ſame to our wayes: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we need not to propoſe a body of Difficulties to be reſolved, but our wiſdome will be, either to avoyd them ſo far as may be by a cleer direction preventing them, or to overcome them when they cannot be avoyded, by ſuch a method as may be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and followed by all that underſtand the Truth of Gods meaning, and their own duty in the Covenant.</p>
                  <p>Thus I have adventured to cut out Work, and offer Tasks to thoſe that ſhall be willing to joyn in compleating this pious Undertaking: not that I preſume to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe or limit any within theſe bounds, or to follow this Method, but that I would give occaſion unto ſuch General hints as theſe are. For unto theſe three Heads of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93868:19"/> 
                     <hi>Principles, Subſtantials,</hi> and <hi>Circumſtantials of Practice,</hi> I ſuppoſe all the Collections which may be made out of our Authors, may be referred; and if this Effect can be obtained in any competent meaſure, I ſhall have what I intended by theſe Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals.</p>
                  <p>Hitherto I have ſpoken of the Body of Practical Divinity, which I conceive will anſwer the requeſt of Forrain Proteſtant Divines made unto us. Now I ſhall come to the Reaſons why it ought to be compiled and imparted unto them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>Of the Second.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>What the Reaſons and Motives are, which ſhould induce us to make up this Body of Divinity, and Communicate it to Forraine Proteſtant Churches.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF to advance this Goſpel-work, there were nothing elſe to move us, but the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the thing it ſelf, and the Call which we have thereunto by forraine Churches, with thoſe Arguments which in their Letter they have alleadged: Truely theſe inducements alone might abundantly ſuffice, and ought to engage us moſt effectually thereunto: for if we have any true zeal to the glory of God, by the Propagation of the Goſpel; if there is any ſincere inclination to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Communion of the Spirit, by the Communication of ſpiritual Gifts and Graces: and if there is any fervency of love toward the Brother hood, or affections of ſerviceableneſs towards the fellow-members of Jeſus Chriſt; all others reaſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thoſe which they offer unto us, will be found ſuperfluous, and of little uſe to perſwade; becauſe the heart that is rightly ſet in heavenly places, and raiſed unto the true Objects which unite the ſame with God, is not acted by earthly Motives, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it may reflect ſometimes not unprofitably upon matters of particular concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>But we find too often (and that to our great grief) when we have to deal even with men that are accounted emninent in the Profeſſion of Religion, and that are of good abilities to judge of all things elſe, that yet thoſe Reaſons which in their own nature are beſt, moſt ſpiritual, and moſt univerſal, are not towards them moſt effectual to perſwade; but the motives which are more particular, more outward and of leſſer worth, doth rather work, and take more powerfully with them. Whether this doth fall out, either becauſe good Men do not alwayes throughly underſtand the beſt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; or becauſe the matter thereof though underſtood, yet is not alwayes mainly and directly intended: or becauſe the Reaſons which are of leſſe worth, are alwayes more level to all mens natural Capacities; Or laſtly, becauſe outward and particular matters are moſt ſuitable to cloſe with humane affections; I will not now ſtand to diſcourſe. What ever the cauſe of this may be, I ſhall endeavour at this time to prevent it, by taking into conſideration both ſorts of Reaſons; that both ſuch who (being truely Spiritual) are in love with Chriſtianity for it ſelf, and ſuch alſo who (walking in a lower Spheere) regard more directly humane and outward relations, may finde in this undertaking, that where with they ought to be affected.</p>
               <p>If we look then before other things upon God, and upon our ſelves as in his hand;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93868:20"/> we may perceive that he doth highly honour us above our reformed Brethren: Chiefly herein, that having received with them the truth of the Goſpel in the purity thereof, we are made partakers above them of this moſt eminent gift of practical knowledg, and enjoy the means thereof more abundantly then any other Church whatſoever: Yet the enjoyment of the moſt eminent of his gifts is not all the Honour which God hath conferred upon us, but he hath cauſed the Excellency of this bleſſing to become ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent unto all the Churches: So that they not onely reſpect, love and eſteem us for the ſame, but they heartily wiſh and deſire for themſelves the ſame favour at Gods hands, and they are moved without envy, to make their application unto us in a friendly manner, that we in love to Gods glory would impart unto them the fruit of that kindneſs which he hath beſtowed upon us. Thus we ſee that he hath not onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eference to himſelf, put Ornaments upon us, to beautifie us with ſalvation, but in reference to our Brethren, he is pleaſed by this means to make us honourable amongſt them; for he doth ſet us forth in their eyes as veſſels which contain the Richeſt of his graces, and by whom he ſeems to be willing to make unto all people his feaſt of the things, full of marrow, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25. 6. and a feaſt of wines on the lees well refined; and leaſt we ſhould not take notice that we are fitted to be ſerviceable in this kinde unto the whole houſhold of faith, he hath moved ſome of the chief members thereof (who are brands pluckt out of the fire of perſecution) to put us in minde of this part of our duty, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing towards us, and calling upon us for the improvement of this peculiar Talent, unto the end for which the Lord hath given the ſame unto us; for they tell us in their Letter; God hath given all his Gifts to every one to profit withall: That to profit with his Gifts is to adminiſter unto others; That we are not the direct owners of his Gift, nor are they our propriety to uſe them as we pleaſe, but all our Title to them is onely this, that we are Stewards thereof to uſe them as he hath appointed us; and as by the right uſe thereof we may expect a great reward and increaſe of Glory to our ſelves; ſo by the abuſe of our truſt, that is, the not uſing of our Talent to bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit others thereby; we ſhall be found unprofitable ſervants, and deſerve both to be deprived of the Grace we have received, and to be caſt off into utter darkneſs where weeping is and gnaſhing of teeth for ever. Thus we ſee they put us to the tryall of our love toward, God, by the diſcovery of our willingneſs to pleaſe him in fulfilling the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nown purpoſe of his will<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> They put us to the trial of our love towards our Brethren, by the manifeſtation of our Reſolution to furniſh them with that which may benefit them to their Edification; They put us to the triall of our faithfulneſs both towards God and Man, by our behaviour in our Stewardſhip and obedience to him that doth imploy us, and our forwardneſs to diſpence his Gifts unto our Brethren, to whom by his appointment we are bound to beſtow them; And they put us unto the tryall of our ſincerity in believing the Promiſes, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earing the Threatnings, by the ſenſe we have of the rewards that ſhall be given to thoſe that uſe rightly, and that abuſe their Talent: And for all this they not only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> before our eyes the thankfulneſs which we owe unto God for the honour he hath conferred upon us more then upon others; but they put us in minde of the wayes by which onely we are enabled to Glorifie God here on Earth amongſt men: by which we are made capable of being glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified with himſelf in heaven hereafter; and by which the Juſtice is maintained, which maketh all the Subjects of his Kingdom through the Holineſs of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ptible and ſenſible of their own and each others happineſs, and without which there w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> little difference between the State of Chriſt, Kingdom and the Kingdom of the World. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> concerning our thankfulneſs towards God for the honour done to us by him, ſeeing our goodneſs cannot be extended unto him. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 16.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93868:20"/> 2. (for no man can be profitable unto God, as he that is wiſe may be profitable unto himſelf, <hi>Job.</hi> 22. 2.) but onely unto the Saints that are in the Earth, and to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ones in whom is all our delight: What other or leſſe acknowledgement can we render unto him, then affectionately to endeavour, that the fruits of his kindneſs towards us may have ſome reflexion back again towards him, by redounding to the comfort of his own deareſt Children.</p>
               <p>And concerning the onely way by which we are enabled to glorifie God on Earth, our Saviour tels us that herein his Father is glorified, that we bear much fruit and ſo become his Diſciples; No man can ſhew forth the Fathers <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 8.</note> Glory otherwiſe, then as it and he is in the Son, nor can any man be in the Son, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then by becoming his Diſciple; nor can any man become his Diſciple otherwiſe but by following him in the way wherein he did glorifie his Father: Whence it is that the Apoſtle teaching us to glorifie God with one mind and mouth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 6, 7. doth ſet Chriſts example before us as the onely rule, bidding us receive one another as Chriſt alſo received us to the glory of God: Now the way by which Chriſt received us to the glory of his Father, was no other but by the imparting of his Fathers Graces, and the free propagation of his goodneſs unto Man-kinde; by this means he hath (as the true Vine) born much fruit, &amp; by this means we alſo ſhall bear much fruit, if here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we become his Diſciples; nor is there any other way on Earth opened but this to glorifie God amongſt men; for all good works, without which no Glory can be given unto God, of what kind ſoever, glorifie him only in this, that they ſhew forth his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and cauſe men to take notice of the excellency of his Nature, that they may have cauſe to admire and love, and praiſe him in the ſame; and if we do nor ſet our hearts entirely to work all our works in God, that he may thus be glorified thereby we have renounced in our heart the great end of our Creation, which is nothing elſe but his glory; and the only means by which that end is attainable, are good works ſhewed forth unto men, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 16. for we are Gods workmanſhip created in Jeſus Chriſt unto Good Works, which God hath before ordained that we ſhould walk in them, that in the ages to come he might ſhew the exceeding Riches of his grace in his kindneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us through Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 7, 10. Thus then the only way to glorifie God the Author of this Talent is to improve it, by imparting unto others freely that which Chriſt hath freely given unto us.</p>
               <p>Nor is there a readier way by which we are made capable of being glorified with God hereafter, then thus to glorifie him on Earth; we ſee the ſlothful ſervant was deprived of glory, becauſe he was ſlothful; and others were made partakers thereof, becauſe they were diligent and faithful in uſing their Talents; and the promiſe is that ſuch as are wiſe ſhall ſhine as the brightnes of the Firmament; and they that turn many unto Righteouſneſs, as the Stars for ever and ever. This then is our wiſdome to win ſouls unto God, and turn many unto Righteouſneſs, and this will prove the greateſt folly, and the greateſt unthankfulneſs that we can be guilty of, that having ſo great a Talent in our hand, and ſo fit for ſuch a ſervice, we ſhould not thereby Honour God by making it uſeful to the enlargement of his Kingdom.</p>
               <p>But above all this, there is a Law of Juſtice which doth require this duty of us as a debt to be paid unto all that are ſuſceptible of the benefit thereof; but chiefly unto thoſe that challenge is as having a right thereunto; all that belong to the houſhold of Faith, have a right to all the priviledges of the houſe, and all the gifts and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures pertaining to it are theirs; all things are yours ſaith the Apoſtle. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 21. 22. becauſe every member of the Body hath an intereſt in all the graces which flow from the head as conferred upon the Body, nor doth any member poſſeſſe any thing for it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93868:21"/> ſelf, but for the whole; nor is any thing in it ſelf, but as it ſtandeth in its place to ſerve the whole, and as it belongeth unto other members; for we are ſaid to be members one of another. So that we have a right to challenge for our uſe, as our own, all the graces which another hath, if we ſtand in need thereof, nor is it lawful for any to refuſe the Communication of any ſpiritual gift wherewith he is poſſeſſed, to any that craveth it of him in the name of Chriſt, except he will make himſelf guilty of the breach of the great and Fundamental law of the Kingdom of Heaven, upon which the happineſs of that whole State is ſettled; for the happineſs of the State of Chriſtianity above all the States of the world is this, that al the Subjects thereof are but one new Creature and Spiritual man in Chriſt, that they are made and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to ſerve one another in Love, as he ſerved us, and to enjoy him in each other, as he is the ſame light of Truth, and light of God in all; for the enjoyments and poſſeſſions of all other men in all other States and Kingdoms of this World are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and peculiar to every one, becauſe ſome things are incommunicably proper to ſome more then to others, as their lot is fallen amongſt men (and except this Law in natural things were obſerved, there would be nothing but endleſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>extricable confuſion and ſtrife, yea much more then now is amongſt the Sons of men) But it is not ſo in Spiritual things; the Spiritual man his joy is this, that others partake of all his bleſſings, that others have a right in him and intereſt, and he in them for all their Grace, and that he is a debtor of all that he hath unto every one, and every one are debtors of all that they have unto him; So that none can count himſelf happy or compleate in any thing, or ought to reſt contented within himſelf, without the Happineſs, Perfection and contentedneſs of others: Thus none can want what another hath; and what God hath given unto any, it is to be offered unto all; and he that doth not live by this Rule in the Church of God, doth exclude his own ſoul from the Communion of Saints, and maketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf incapable of all the Felicities of Chriſts Kingdom. We ſee then how many and how ſtrong the obligations are, which bind us unto this duty of Spiritual Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the graces which we have received to profit withall; for if we ſhould not intend this, we ſhall diſcover our ſelves to be of all men the moſt ingrateful towards God, and moſt unworthy of all the Honours which he hath caſt upon us; We ſhall ſhew our ſelves deſtitute of all love, both to God and man, and of all faithfulneſs in the truſt committed unto us, of all ſincerity in our Profeſſion, and of all care either to advance Gods glory as becometh the Diſciples of Chriſt, or to be advanced unto glory by him, or to maintain the happineſs of our own Eſtate by fellowſhip with his members, or finally to diſcharge the debt of Righteouſneſs which we owe unto others on Gods behalf; for God hath aſſigned the payment of all the debts which we owe unto him, which are the fruits of his Graces towards us, to be laid out upon the members of Jeſus Chriſt, that much joy and many thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings from many hearts and mouths, may redound to the glory of the Father through him. If then we ſhould hold this truth of God in unrighteouſneſs, we ſhould not onely be found enemies to God and our ſelves, ſo far as in us lyeth to fruſtrate him of his intent, and our ſelves of all the honour whereunto he doth deſign us, but oppoſite unto all goodneſs, to ſuppreſſe the brightneſs of his glory, to darken the comforts of his Children, to defraud our Brethren of their juſt claim and expectation, and to deprive all ſorts of men of that wherein we are indebted unto them; for it is not onely our Brethren (that challenge that which is their right, of us, on Gods behalf) to whom we owe this duty as a debt, but we owe it unto all men; that either now, or in after ages may profit thereby, towards the advancement of Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93868:21"/> and that is the thing which our Brethren in the concluſion of their Letter, preſſe (though briefly yet throughly) upon us: for having propoſed Gods intention in giving his Gifts, our duty anſwerable thereunto, and their demand grounded upon both they preſent unto us the benefits which enſue our performance of their requeſt, which are all the effects of the truth which is in the Goſpel, as by it ſelf it is uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full unto all ſorts of perſons, young and old, Teachers and thoſe that are taught, Godly and ungodly, Peaceable and contentious: True Profeſſors and thoſe that erre from the Truth, whether by Hypocriſie, or Security, or Obſtinacy; and in a word to all men, aſwell of this age as of that which ſhall ariſe hereafter, all the advantages of Inſtruction, Direction, correction, comfort, Reproof and conviction, tending to ſet forward peace and joy, through Righteouſneſs and Holineſs in the ſouls of men, or whatſoever bleſſing elſe, any ſhall ſtand in need of in their ſeveral conditions: all this I ſay, we are Debtors to procure unto them, by the means which are put in our hands to that effect; for at this time both God and Men do call upon us to make this uſe of our Peculiar Talent of the word of life, in holding it forth unto them.</p>
               <p>If therefore we ſhould hide our Talent, and put this candle which the Lord hath lighted among us to give light unto all that are in the houſe, under a buſhel, that is, if we condeſcend not to this their deſire, we ſhall wrong all the Churches; we ſhall rob theſe in particular that ſue for it of what is their due: and as much as in us lieth we ſhall make the word of Truth ineffectual, and ſhew our ſelves adverſaries to his vertue and the manifeſtation thereof: which how the Lord will in the End take at our hands, I ſhall not need to mention. But I ſhall heartily rather pray that in love to himſelf and to his Truth, our ſpirits may be ſtirred up to behave our ſelves in the opportunity of doing this ſervice as ſhall be moſt anſwerable unto our own happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the glory and the kingdom of Chriſt whereunto we are called.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the conſiderations which from the nature of the Duty it ſelf ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce us to the performance thereof, which our Brethren in their Letter having onely touched and pointed at, I have thought good a little further thus to enlarge, that whatever ſhall be undertaken in this kind, may proceed from the right Principle and frame of heart, which will make the work acceptable unto God and profitable unto thoſe that go about it. For if the work be not intended upon theſe grounds, and upon theſe alone, directly and principally without worldly conſiderations and humane Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects as leading Motives, it will find but ſmall ſucceſs, and little conduct from the Spirit of grace to give it a furtherance, becauſe no enterpriſe can have more ſtrength then its chief Aim and Object can give it.</p>
               <p>And although ſome other Arguments of this nature and to the ſame effect might be alledged, or the ſame might be further inſiſted upon, perhaps not unprofitably; yet becauſe theſe Motives are the chief to which all others may be referred, and ſo evident that they cannot (as I conceive) be denyed, and of ſuch efficacy (if laid to heart) that where they take not, none other in this kind are like to perſwade; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall not inſiſt any further upon them, but come to the ſecond ſort of Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which in order unto theſe foregoing may perhaps adde ſomething to our zeal and reſolution as it proceedeth from a mixt affection; which even good men are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable ſometime to entertain rather as they are men, then as they are the Children of the moſt High, depending immediately upon his Will.</p>
               <p>If we look then in the ſecond place upon our ſelves as we are amongſt the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Goſpel, engaged not only to maintain the credit of the Profeſſion, but to advance the Reformation of the Churches both at home and abroad, and to concurre with Forrain Proteſtants to aſſiſt the Common Cauſe of Religion againſt the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93868:22"/> thereof, we ſhall find nothing more ſutable to the credit of our Profeſſion, or more advantagious to our own and others reformation, or more effectual in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence to aſſiſt Forrainers in the Common Cauſe, then the Compleating of this Body of Practical Divinity will be.</p>
               <p>The Credit of our Profeſſion doth include a twofold Notion: the one doth look at the Profeſſion in it ſelf, the other at us as Profeſſors: in both theſe, there is ſome matter of Credit to be upheld as to men. In reference to the Profeſſion, we are bound in conſcience (ſeeing we believe it to be the ſaving Truth of God) to make it Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and Honourable before all men, approving it unto the conſcience to be ſuch as we believe it to be. And in reference to our-ſelves, the good opinion others have of our ſincerity, zeal and ability in the way of the Profeſſion, doth oblige us in honeſty to endeavour to the utmoſt to anſwer their expectation, and maintain the Honour of our good name in relation to our Religion. In theſe reſpects I ſay, the compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Practical Body of Divinity will be of ſpecial uſe, as well for the honour of the Profeſſion, as for our credit in upholding it.</p>
               <p>For whereas nothing doth ſo much either ſcandalize the weak, or ſtagger the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, at the profeſſion of the Proteſtant Religion, or give advantage on the one hand unto the Papiſts to ſeduce ſilly ſouls to a ſuperſtitious worſhip, as this reproach, <hi>That we are all broken to pieces among our-ſelves, and divided in our ſenſe about Religion, having no certainty in any thing:</hi> on the other hand unto the ſelf-conceited Libertines, to entice high minded Zelots to the pride of ſingular Saintſhip, as this other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach; <hi>That we rest in practice of formes; and being deſtitute of the power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, have nothing that is ſpiritual in our Profeſſion:</hi> Whereas (I ſay) both theſe Adverſaries labour different ways, and upon colourable pretences (taken from parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular miſdemeanors wrongfully applyed unto the whole ſubſtance of Religion) to diſcredit and blemiſh the profeſſion of the truth (which we Miniſters are chiefly bound to uphold) there can be no courſe either more anſwerable to the nature of our Calling, or ſo proper to ſtop the mouths of theſe Adverſaries, or ſo fit to ſettle the wavering thoughts of unſtable ſouls, or more effectual to vindicate the credit of the Profeſſion from the aſperſions of diviſion, of uncertainty, of formality, and of the want of ſpiritual power, then to make up this Practical Body of Divinity. For it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compoſed of thoſe many Poſitive doctrines which are undeniably evident in the Scriptures, which being underſtood will be cleer to the conſcience by their own light, which will manifeſt all the true grounds of ſpiritual knowledge, not fantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally but with real demonſtrations, and which unanimouſly all Proteſtants will fully acknowledge to be the ſubſtance of their Profeſſion and Religion: I ſay, thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines being gathered into a full body, will ſtand as an uncontroulable witneſs for the credit of the Truth againſt all theſe injurious reproaches.</p>
               <p>Nor can it be imagined that in the great multitude and variety of particular Opinions, in the manifold diſputes, and inconſiderate heats of men about matters extra-fundamental, and in the different practiſes of things which are but circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial, a way of Peace and Unity ſhould either be found for our ſelves, or ſhewed unto others, by any other means then by a demonſtration of our agreement in all truths and duties which are neceſſary for Salvation in reſpect of God, and profitable for edification in reſpect of one another: And this is that which our Brethren in the Latter part of their letter hint at, when they tell us that ſuch a body of Divinity will not onely be ſerviceable for Schollars, but even for Teachers, to furniſh them with more uſefull matter in their Sermons then now they are able to find in the books of controverſie, whereunto almoſt all their Learning is reduced, repreſenting unto us
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93868:22"/> the evil which befalleth moſt of their Churches: <hi>viz.</hi> that they are overwhelmed with matters of Controverſie: that their controverſal writings are void of Piety, full of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs, and no ways tending to edification: And that their young Schollers of Divinity being trained up to this way of contentious Learning, for want of better Teaching, prove in the courſe of their Miniſtry very often void of all Charitableneſs, and ſtrangers to peaceable Affections. Which evils by our Pious aſſiſtance and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours they hope may be remedied, if we would gather out of our Authors who handle matters of Divinity in a Practical way as they relate to conſcience; a full and ſound body of ſaving and ſavory truths, which may be put into their hands to waken them unto Righteouſneſs. For they conceive not amiſs that by Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſuch an Inſtrument of knowledge and way of Teaching which it will produce, may not onely ſeaſon their ſpirits with meek and humble thoughts concerning themſelves, and with loving, kind and merciful affections towards their Neighbours (which will make them peaceable) but may work upon them the power of Godlineſs, when they ſhall perceive how the Theoretical and neceſſary Truths of Faith which they make now matters of ſtrife, and have diſregarded as to their true uſefulneſs, ought to be applied unto their own and other mens conſciences, to teach them to walk with God in all their wayes.</p>
               <p>And indeed this is a ſad matter, which not onely thoſe Churches groan under, but all the reſt more or leſſe, have cauſe to bemoan: That becauſe many in the Miniſtry do ſpend their ſtrength and wit upon needleſſe and curious diſpenſations about mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of private opinion, rather then upon the application of known and neceſſary Doctrines unto conſcience, becauſe theſe diſputations are agitated with more provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to heat and animoſity, then to regular and modeſt ſearches after the way to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve doubts impartially; and becauſe the ſmalleſt differences of opinions beget or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily the extreameſt differences of affections, when men ſtudy no Rules of mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in reſpect of Paſſions, or of being wiſe to Sobriety in reſpect of contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or of mutual forbearance in reſpect of actions (all which are things if not hated, yet ſuſpected, ſlighted and neglected almoſt every where in this age) I ſay becauſe theſe diſorders (which like weeds in a Garden not weeded, overgrow the Church) have taken place almoſt every where; it is very doleful to ſee, that the main and great truths of the Profeſſion are extreamly neglected and not at all Cultivated; and that by this means, the adverſaries (who lie in wait to deceive the ſimple, and watch to diſcredit our Religion) do get all the advantages which almoſt they can deſire, to bring their ends to paſſe upon us, and diſreſpect upon our Profeſſion; for when the frames of matters are diſcompoſed, as now they are in all the Churches (by reaſon of the alterations which are brought upon the States of the world:) it is no great difficulty for cunning men, to work Siniſter impreſſions, and thoughts of contempt againſt our Profeſſion, upon weak Spirits, who know not the ſubſtance and true grounds of our Religion; but look onely (as moſt men do) ſuperficially upon the outward appearance, and the worſt ſide of other mens behaviours and fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
               <p>For theſe cauſes, if we have any ſenſe of Honour for the Truth, and if we have any deſire as in conſcience we are bound to have, to maintain the Credit of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and to free it from the occaſions of all theſe prejudices, we ſhould ſet our ſelves earneſtly to hold forth, upon the Common and undenyable grounds of Truth, the ſubſtantial Excellency of the Doctrine of Piety, which by the making up of this Practical Body of Divinity may be done, and by none other way ſo effectually.</p>
               <p>As for our own credit amongſt our brethren in reference to the Profeſſion, if we
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93868:23"/> ſtudy not to maintain it in Gods way, by the Propagation of the Truth wherewith we are intruſted, certainly God will blaſt it more then ever it hath been raiſed; Nor can we expect that any thing will uphold our Reputation in Gods way, amongſt our Brethren, ſo much, as the ſatisfaction which they expect, and we ought to give unto them in this their deſire; for herein they put us unto the real proof of our ſincerity, whether or no we are willing to do any thing for the Faith, and for them; and if in this we fail them, we ſhall deſerve to loſe our Credit with them, and that moſt juſtly.</p>
               <p>The Miniſters of the Churches of Great Brittane have always been eſteemed by the reſt of the reformed Proteſtants, to be ſound in judgement, learned in the way of Piety, and zealous in the practice thereof, moderate in their affections, and diſcreet in their writings againſt Diſſentors: Therefore in the work of reconciliation between the Lutherans &amp; the Reformed Churches, they were never excepted againſt by either ſide, but rather accepted as Mediators of the difference by both ſides, but chiefly by the ſide which is beſt reformed, whoſe confidence towards us, and eſteem of us is clearly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted by the tenor of this letter which hath been written to us about the body of Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Divinity; for therein with a great deal of modeſty and humility, they not only defer a great deal of reſpect unto the worth that God hath put upon us, but they invite us to receive the Honour of being their leaders to Godlineſs, and their Teachers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to after ages; and although we may not without preſumption, think the better of our ſelves, becauſe others prefer us in Honour to themſelves, or have any high thoughts of our own ſufficiency (for who is ſufficient for ſuch things? and Chriſt we know is the only leader and teacher) becauſe our Brethren eſteem highly of us by ſubmiſſion unto the Grace of God in us; yet if there be any truth of generoſity in our Spirits, or any reſentment of duty towards ſuch as love us in the Lord, we cannot be inſenſible of ſo mighty a provocation as this unto love and good works, but with all zeal, in true Humility, giving glory unto God, we are bound to the utmoſt of our abilities to impart our ſelves unto them: not ſo much that they may not ſeem deceived in us, and we found unworthy of the Honour given to us; but that the free gift of Grace may be exalted in the Communion of Saints, and God alone glorified thereby. Even amongſt morall men it is true, that Commendations adde life unto vertue; and that as the beſt things in their nature are moſt Communicable; ſo it is one of the chiefeſt delights of the beſt natures to Communicate the ſame, not ſo much to gain praiſe, as to do that which is good in it ſelf, and praiſe-worthy; which is the contentment of a vertuous diſpoſition; and if this is true in morall diſpoſitions, how much more ought it to be in thoſe that are Spiritual: if therefore there be any vertue, if there be any praiſe, let us think not only how to make good the eſteem which they have of us, but rather to do that which is good and commendable, as it is acceptable unto God and approved of men; for upon this ground the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 8. doth recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend unto our care and ſtudy, all things that are true, all things that are honeſt, all things that are juſt, all things that are pure, all things that are lovely, and all things that are of good report; and that in reſpect of vertue, and in reſpect of praiſe: And if in this work which we are now exhorting to be undertaken, all theſe Motives concur at once, ſo fully and ſo eminently as in nothing more; and that not in a private but in a publick reſpect; then it followeth, that if there be any vertue or ſenſe of praiſe to be regarded in order to the holy profeſſion, which only is our glory, that we will not ſuffer our Reputation to fall to the ground by a careleſs neglect of ſo manifeſt a duty, wherein our credit not only is ſo deeply engaged, but our Religion it ſelf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly concerned: So that if upon theſe motives and conſiderations, this buſineſſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93868:23"/> ſhould not at all be effected, it would not only be an Argument of a moſt brutiſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibility and ſtupidity in us towards that which is true honour; but it would clearly evince the unſoundneſſe of our hearts in the Profeſſion it ſelf, when we ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſo careleſſe of maintaining and propagating the truth thereof, that even with the loſs of our reputation, and the loſs of the love of thoſe that have ſued to us for this duty, we ſhould ſuffer it to be blaſted and lie under contempt, when it is in our power to Vindicate, both it and our ſelves from reproaches.</p>
               <p>And thus much concerning the point of reputation; The next Motive in this kind is the advancement of the Reformation of the Churches, both at home and abroad; a thing which doth mainly concern us, a thing whereunto we are deeply engaged, and a thing whereunto this work will be very conducible; for as concerning the Churches abroad; that it will be a profitable inſtrument in their hand, to ſet forward the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation which they ſtand in need of, we can have no greater proof then their own Confeſſion in their Letter; For this is the very ground why they make it their ſuite unto us, that ſuch a Body of Divinity may be compiled, becauſe they expect from it and by it; an effectual means to take away the chief cauſes of their Diſtractions and Diſorders in Spiritual things. And becauſe our own Diſorders in ſome kind here at home, in ſtead of being Reformed, have increaſed of late, and do proceed from the ſame diſeaſes which have begotten theirs; therefore in procuring a Remedy for our ſelves, we may hope to become helpful unto them alſo.</p>
               <p>Now that this Body of Practical Divinity will be very uſeful to this purpoſe, may be gathered from the nature of our diſeaſe, and the property of the cure to Remedy the ſame.</p>
               <p>The diſeaſes which afflict us, proceed from the ignorance and diſtempers of our minde in things pertaining to God, and from the unrulineſſe of walking in things pertaing to Men: This ignorance in the underſtanding, and diſtemper in the will, and unrulineſſe in the outward man, is fomented by the ſlight and cunning crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſome men of corrupt minds, who being reprobate concerning the Faith (as not adhereing to the Teſtimony of Jeſus in the Word, which is the rule thereof) and having taken up either a Superſtitious and Traditional formality, or a ſingular and ſelf-conceited Spirituality of worſhip and of godlineſſe, they deny the power and reſiſt the truth of both, by taking away the grounds, and making void the Common Profeſſion of Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>Theſe men both ſuperſtitiouſly and ſingularly affected, ſeeking to get followers unto their ſeverall wayes and opinions, agree to waſt the Churches, and to blaſt with a peſtilent breath all that is not conformable to their practice, if they can finde any ſmall colour for raiſing Calumnies againſt it; and thus they fill the Churches with diſputes, and the heads of ignorant people with profane and vain bablings, which dayly increaſe unto more ungodlineſſe: For by this means ſcandals are multiplyed, the unity of the Spirit diſſolved, the bonds of peace neglected, factions ſet on foot and continued with animoſity, wherein the weaker ſort as Children are toſſed too and fro, and carried about with every wind of Doctrine, till they loſe their hold of all Principles, and then give themſelves over to Atheiſm.</p>
               <p>This is the nature of our diſeaſes both at home and abroad; therefore the Remedy for both will be the ſame, which can be none other but to this effect.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that the faithful Miniſters and Profeſſors of the Goſpel, both there and here, ſhould ſtand faſt together in one Spirit and one mind; ſtriving together in one way for the faith of the Goſpel, and in nothing terrified by their adverſaries.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that they ſhould both with one conſent agree upon ſome profitable way
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:93868:24"/> of handling neceſſary and uſeful Controverſies, and of ſhunning profane and vain bablings, and the contradiction of Science falſly ſo called.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that we and they ſhould endeavour by all poſſible means to fight againſt our ſpiritual adverſaries with the ſword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God: holding out unto the World the ſame form of ſound words, and dividing the Doctrine of Truth rightly in one and the ſame way of preaching and handling the Scriptures to advance godlineſs, as it becometh workmen that need not to be aſhamed.</p>
               <p>And to enable us all joyntly to endeavour theſe things; I am very confident that next unto the graces of the Spirit, and the infallible word of truth, delivered unto us in the Scriptures (which are the two things which God hath Covenanted to continue with the Miniſtry unto the end of the World, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 49. 21.) I ſay next unto theſe two, I am confident that no means can be uſed to enable us unto that endeavour more fitly, and with Gods ordinary bleſſing more ſucceſsfully, then this Body of Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Divinity, if it were compiled and communicated in Engliſh to our men at home, and in Latin to thoſe that are abroad.</p>
               <p>For the three parts of this Body, if they were throughly and fully handled (as from our Authors they may be) will meet directly and in a right order with the three main and Original cauſes of our diſorderlineſſe and diſtracted condition, to ſhew the Spiritual wayes of Reforming the ſame, wherein if we ſhall agree to walk unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly, as no doubt we will, we may undoubtedly alſo believe, thar by this Union we ſhall to all our adverſaries become not only invincible but irreſiſtible to work the overthrow of Satans Kingdom. And this ſhall ſuffice alſo concerning this point of Reformation, which is to be advanced by this means: and which the faithful Miniſtry of this Land is bound to endeavour by the Tenor of their ſolemn League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in the preſence of God, who hath put the means of this in our hand to be effected, and now calleth upon us to make uſe of the ſame.</p>
               <p>The laſt thing which I mentioned, whereunto we are engaged, and whereunto this Body of Divinity will be effectual, is to concur with Forrain Proteſtants in the Common cauſe of Religion, and to aſſiſt them againſt the Common Enemies thereof. This Concurrence and aſſiſtance is an engagement that doth lie cloſer to us then I find it apprehended by many: Therefore I ſhall endeavour to repreſent unto thoſe that are Conſcionable in matters of publick concernment, not ſo much what help may be given to the cauſe by this means, for that may be clearly ſeen by what is ſaid already, but what the obligation is which ſhould make us Concurre with Forrain Proteſtants to uphold the profeſſion of the cauſe.</p>
               <p>As con cerning the aſſiſtance which this work will yield unto the Cauſe, if we will adde any thing to that which hath been ſaid already concerning the Credit of the Profeſſion, which it will help to uphold, and concerning the Reformation of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, which it will help to take away, we may conſider two things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, What properly the common Cauſe is.</p>
               <p>Secondly, What it is that weakens our hands in proſecuting of it.</p>
               <p>If the Common Cauſe of Proteſtants be made any thing elſe then the Propagating of the light of the Goſpel, which is atteſted in the Scriptures, that the Kingdom and life of Jeſus Chriſt may take place in the ſouls of all men, to the Glory of God the Father, by the graces of his Spirit, it is fouly miſtaken.</p>
               <p>For all that we have proteſted for in former time againſt Popery, is this, that we will not be led by the dictates of other men, to believe and practiſe upon implicit faith and blind obedience what they preſcribe to us in matters of Religion, but that in ſuch matters we will knowingly rely onely upon the Word of God revealed in the holy Scriptures, to follow the dictates thereof.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:93868:24"/>
               <p>And as we are bound ſtill to continue this Profeſſion againſt Popery on the one hand; ſo in theſe diſtracted times eſpecially, we are obliged to adde a further Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation to clear the truth of our profeſſion on the other hand, which is this, that as we think it not lawfull for us to give up our faith to other men, ſo we conceive it nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther acceptable to God, nor ſafe for us to be led by the dictates of our own imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations alone to believe and practice ſingularly and by our ſelves, whatever in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion we ſhall in our own private conceit fancy to be right; but that we will rationally entertain and handle the word of God in the holy Scriptures, for the underſtanding and practiſing of all Religious Truths offered and duties preſcribed unto us therein: that is to ſay, that we will not interpret the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures in matter of outward duty and performance, contrary to the Common grounds of reaſon and righteous order amongſt men; and in matters of inward relation to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, that we will be wiſe unto Sobriety, conceiving that to be the truth of the Spirit, which is moſt anſwerable to the common Principles of the Faith of all ages, and to the Spiritual ſtate of holy Communion which Jeſus Chriſt hath ſetled in the new Covenant between God and all his Members.</p>
               <p>The common Cauſe of Proteſtants hath theſe four main intereſts in Chriſtianity, by which it upholdeth the truth thereof, and thereby is diſtinguiſhable from all other Profeſſions.</p>
               <p>The Firſt is, The intereſt of Scripture knowledge.</p>
               <p>The Second is, The intereſt of the life of the Spirit.</p>
               <p>The Third is, The intereſt of orderly walking in all Gods Ordinances, Natural and Spiritual.</p>
               <p>The Fourth is, The intereſt of the Communion of Churches in reference to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual edification in theſe forenamed matters.</p>
               <p>Theſe intereſts being all joyned and profeſſedly followed (that is, openly owned without offence as it becometh the Diſciples of Chriſt) make up the true Proteſtant Cauſe, that is, the profeſſion of Chriſtianity: And if any one of theſe be not followed, the Cauſe is ſo far deſerted, as it is neglected.</p>
               <p>By Scripture knowledge (which is the Fundamental Rule and Seed of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſtianity) Proteſtants were begotten and are diſtinguiſhed from Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</p>
               <p>By the life of the Spirit (which is the heart and ſoul of the profeſſion of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity) Proteſtants do grow up in Chriſt who is their head, till they ſhall come to a perfect man: and are diſtinguiſhed from Socinians and all ſuch as turn Chriſtianity into a Moral profeſſion of a new kind of Philoſophy, which is refined and entertained upon revealed Principles, but in effect nothing beſides or above humane Reaſoning.</p>
               <p>By the orderly walking in all Gods Ordinances (which is the viſible body of the profeſſion of Chriſtianity) Proteſtants ſtand firm in the truth, to bear witneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of unto the world, and are diſtinguiſhed from all Libertines that pretend to be ſo ſpiritual as to be above all Ordinances.</p>
               <p>And by the Communion of Churches (which is the activity of this viſible body) Proteſtants are ſtrengthned in their growth and teſtimony, made invincible againſt their adverſaries, made helpful to each other, and the cauſe, and diſtinguiſhed from all thoſe that pretend to the ſingularity of Saintſhip in their ſeveral ways by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves alone, with the condemnation of ſuch as go not along with them.</p>
               <p>Theſe being the true intereſts of this Cauſe as it is ſubordinate unto Chriſtianity, and Chriſtianity being taken up upon none other ground but as it is revealed in the holy Scriptures, nor maintained to any other End, but to manifeſt the life of Jeſus
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:93868:25"/> Chriſt by his kingdom unto the world, it is clear that the whole obſervation of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Ordinances and the practice of mutual Communion, which are the two latter intereſts of the Cauſe, muſt riſe from the firſt, and reſt in the ſecond of thoſe which are the former: and whatſoever deſignes, practices, negotiations and undertakings are ſaid to be for Chriſtianity or the Proteſtant Religion (which are all one) and do not attend to advance directly, either Scripture, knowledge or the life of the Spirit, or the walking under Ordinances, or the Communion of Churches, or do tend ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly to advance any one of theſe without a reference to all the reſt, they are to be judged falſe, deceitful and deſtructive to the cauſe and truth of Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>Therefore we ought to acknowledge none to be a ſervant to the Cauſe of Chriſt (that is a true Proteſtant) but he who walketh by this Rule of the new creature; and upon ſuch be peace and upon the Iſrael of God.</p>
               <p>As for me; I ſhall by Gods grace never entertain any deſignes and practices, or favour any motions and pretences which are undertaken and proſecuted with ſubtilty or with a ſtrong hand againſt the perſons of a party diſagreeing from judgement, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this ground becauſe they favour not my way; but I ſhall make the proſecution of their forenamed intereſts, as by ſpiritual means and wayes they are approveable to the conſcience of every rational man, the open and onely rule of my walking in this Cauſe. And if any man ſhall find me ſtraying from this path, and ſhew me that I am not in it, he will oblige me to thank him for converting a Sinner from the error of his Way.</p>
               <p>Hitherto I have given you my ſenſe of the Common Cauſe of Proteſtants; Now I ſhall adde a word or two concerning that which I ſuppoſe doth weaken our hands in proſecuting of it: And that is partly an ordinary miſtake; partly an univerſal neglect of Duty in the Actors for it.</p>
               <p>The miſtake is in two things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That moſt meaning well to the Proteſtant Cauſe, as they do underſtand it, act all rather againſt the adverſaries thereof then for the Cauſe it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That when they act ſo, they take up no rule of Reaſon and Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in dealing with adverſaries for their good, or upon grounds of Juſtice, but give way to Paſſion and Hatred; and all that is imagined to be hurtful to them, is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be advantagious to themſelves: both which are courſes altogether prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous unto Chriſtianity. For the true way of advancing Chriſtianity is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive but edificative: that is, doth not intend to overthrow and build at leiſure afterward, as the Method of ſome is: but it doth intend to build firſt Chriſts kingdom, that thereby it may overthrow the frame of Satans Policy: for it holdeth forth the word of life and truth, that by the manifeſtation of light it may diſpell error and darkneſs; And when this is done, then it proceeds to the condemnation of the wayes of unrighteouſneſs: firſt it bringeth our thoughts unto the obedience of Chriſt, that then every ſtrong Hold of Satan, and every imagination and high thing which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alteth it ſelf againſt the knowledge of God may be caſt down: for except we bring Chriſt with us, and ſet him a working upon the Spirits of men that are in the ſnares of Satan, and led captive at his pleaſure, we ſhall never be able to bind the ſtrong man that hath poſſeſſion of their ſouls: and far leſs ſhall we be able to ſpoil him of his goods, which are the luſts and the inclinations of the fleſh, whereby he doth act ſelf will in them, that they may not be ſubject to the will of God.</p>
               <p>The way then of Chriſtianity is more directly Poſitive then Negative; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a miſtake to think that the refuting and oppoſing of adverſaries is the main buſineſs which ought to be proſecuted in theſe times: but a far greater miſtake it is, to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:93868:25"/> think that by making the wayes of our adverſaries odious, or by vexing their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and prejudging them any way, (by hook or crook as we uſe to ſay) in the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and conveniencies of profeſſing their Tenets, we ſhall profit our Cauſe, or gain much upon or againſt them. No ſurely: for this is a far greater Miſtake then the other; and yet this is the ordinary practice which is moſt commonly followed by thoſe who are zealous for the Cauſe. But this way cannot porſibly prove ſucceſſefull, becauſe it doth quite miſtake the intereſt of Chriſtianity, which is nothing elſe but by the knowledge of the Scriptures and the life of the Spirit to bring men to walk orderly before God and men, and live in the Communion which the Members of Chriſt owe to each other. And if we aim not at this even towards our Adverſaries to bring them hereunto, we deal not with them as Chriſtians ought to do, but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake our profeſſion. Now it is neither the convincing them of their particular Errors without further inſtruction, nor the laying open of their ſhame, nor the vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Spirits by troubling their perſons, or ſtoping their profeſſions that will bring them to any of theſe holy duties which uphold the truth of Chriſtianity, but this way of dealing will rather ſet them further off in their Affections, both from the love of the truth and from us: ſo that when we ſhall offer them means tending directly to that which is truely their way to life, they will reject the ſame, only becauſe they come from that hand which hath made it ſelf utterly hateful unto them.</p>
               <p>Theſe miſtakes weaken the Cauſe greatly; but the univerſal neglect which is in Two main things, doth it far more.</p>
               <p>The Firſt is, The neglect of duty in uſing ſpiritual means, and in a ſpiritual way to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Diſſenters.</p>
               <p>The Second is, The neglect of brotherly Communion in ſpiritual things, which is the laſt point of the main intereſt of the Cauſe.</p>
               <p>The firſt neglect which is of the means ſutable to the proſecution of the Cauſe doth proceed from the forenamed miſtakes, which indeed make ſome Profeſſors man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age Proteſtancy as a State Religion, rather then a true profeſſion of Chriſtianity: and ſo they take their ſtrength (chiefly againſt Diſſenters) from State-Authority and practices ſubordinate thereunto in a worldly way of Policy rather then from the work of God and the work of the Spirit. And becauſe many of the active men who have parts, and ſo love to appear in the Front and to take matters upon them, have been byaſſed this way, ſome for one, ſome for another intereſt of State, making themſelves and all matters of Religion ſubſervient thereunto: therefore it hath pleaſed God to befool them in their Counſels, and to ſuffer Statan to ſet Inſtruments awork who have out acted them in all theſe wayes: but if they had walked by Faith in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity, according to the Rules of the Goſpel within their own Sphere, &amp; not according to worldly wiſdom; if they had in a cauſe of Chriſtianity made uſe of none other means but of thoſe which Chriſt hath uſed and ſanctified unto them, and in that way by which he and his Apoſtles have ſhewed us they ſhould be uſed, they ſhould not have miſcarried as they have done, by truſting to the arm of fleſh, nor could Satan either have over-reached them in their Counſels, or ſtopped them in their proceedings which now he hath been able to do, becauſe he is of old Maſter of the Trade of policy and power, which they of late as young Prentices were beginning to take up; and this is ſo undeniably evident to any that will trace Publick proceedings in ſome actors, and compare them with the Rules of Chriſtianity, that I am (for my Brethrens ſake) aſhamed to ſpeak of it any more: and ſhall therefore turn my back upon particulars to cover them with ſilence as my fathers nakedneſs, nor ſhall I mention any more of this neglect in the general, leſt I ſhould ſeem either
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:93868:26"/> to reproach thoſe with their failings, who by admonition may be reclaimed from the error of their way, or to furniſh the adverſaries with matter of contempt againſt the Cauſe, by reaſon of our frailties who mannage the ſame.</p>
               <p>The other neglect which is of Brotherly Communion in Spiritual matters, both amongſt our ſelves at home and toward the Churches abroad, is of all others the greateſt hinderance to the Cauſe, and obſtruction to the wayes of Goſpel-edification. For if brotherly Communion were not neglected, all the former miſtakes and neglects might be remedied by common advice: but becauſe it is not at all laid to heart, no remedy can either be applyed, or being offered become effectual. For now although ſome can diſcern the cauſes of our miſeries, and know where the Remedy thereof is to be found, and how to be made uſe of; yet becauſe our ſpiritual gifts are like dead mens bones ſcattered at the graves mouth, diſ-joynted, withered, buried within every mans particular breſt, without life and without coherence for the actions of life: therefore we are unſerviceable one to another, nor can there be any common Cure applyed to common Diſeaſes. For as the body of the Church cannot otherwiſe be edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied then by it ſelf through love, when every joynt ſupplyeth according to the effectual working in the meaſure of every part, that which maketh the increaſe of the body: ſo the evils and diſtempers of the parts, which are deſtructive to the whole, cannot otherwiſe be taken away, but by the ſpiritual communion of gifts, and the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of Graces from one member to another. For which cauſe I have made it my work for theſe many years to ſolicite the performance of this duty, and continue ſtill in ſo doing where ever I can get any opportunity to repreſent the neceſſity thereof. And although my earneſt and conſtant Solicitations have not been ſo effectual as I could wiſh, yet I muſt bleſſe God that they have not been altogether without effect; for although there is not much appearing outwardly, yet ſome grounds are laid which I am confident the gates of hell will never be able to ſhake.</p>
               <p>It cannot be denyed but that moſt men are yet full of their own counſels, and therefore conſider not what is ſuggeſted or may be ſuggeſted by others; moſt men are full of their own ſtrength; and many of thoſe that preach ſelf-denyal unto others, practice in ſpiritual matters leaſt of it themſelves, and therefore they look not out for mutual ſupply of ſtrength from the brotherly communion of Graces; but all men al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt do pleaſe themſelves in their own way, ſo that they regard no man furtherthen he doth come up and follow the way of their particular chooſing, becauſe the Apoſtolical Rule and practice that <hi>being free from all, we ſhould become ſervants unto all, 1 Cor.</hi> 9. 19. is for the moſt part not at all regarded. I ſay it cannot be denyed, but that for the moſt part as yet things are ſo; But when he who is now in action, ſhall have accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed to ſcatter the Holy People, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 17. ſo that none of that ſtrength which Worldly-wiſe men have hitherto put their confidence in, ſhall be either ſhut up or left any more with them; <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 36. then their care will be opened to believe theſe Suggeſtions, and acknowledge this to be a truth, that <hi>Chriſt is their Rock ſo far as they depend upon him, and act joyntly in his way, and no further.</hi> And if once this principle be entertained and made a Maxime to walk by in every thing, they will finde that the Lord will ſuddenly appear as Judge for his People, and ſpeedily repent him for his Servants. But till we leave all the confidences which by our own devices we have choſen to our ſelves, and till we have freed our ſpirits from the deluſions and the jealouſies which we have framed unto our ſelves, to ſanctifie the Lord alone in our hearts, and to make him our confidence and our fear by walking in his way, we cannot look for any proſperity, or expect that he ſhould appear amongſt us.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:93868:26"/>
               <p>Now his way is the way of brotherly and holy Communion, to maintain the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his truth in the Scriptures, the life of his Spirit in the Covenant, and the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of his Ordinances in the Church; And whatſoever Counſel we follow, or courſe we take which doth not lead us to the one End in this way, will never bring any comfort with it; And I may freely ſay, Becauſe this Counſel and courſe hath not only been neglected by all, but flighted and deſpiſed by ſome, therefore the Lord hath not as yet appeared amongſt us.</p>
               <p>Thus we have ſeen what properly the Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtant Cauſe is, and what it is that weakens our hands in proſecuting the ſame. Now if we look back upon the Body of Practical Divinity which hath been delineated, to conſider what aſſiſtance and help we may give thereby unto the Proteſtant Cauſe, in caſe we ſhall deſire to concur with the forrain Churches of Chriſt therein, we ſhall find that it ſhall prove one of the moſt profitable inſtruments that can be made uſe of, to maintain all the parts and intereſts of the Cauſe, and that hardly any thing can be ſet on foot, that will be more ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able both to certifie the miſtakes which make us miſcarry in our undertakings for Chriſtianity, and to ſet us upon the duties, without which the way of our Profeſſion cannot ſucceſsfully be proſecuted.</p>
               <p>For if you reflect upon the intereſts of the Cauſe, and take notice what fitneſs this Engine will have to maintain the ſame; you ſhall perceive, that both by the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the matter and form thereof, and by the application of the whole to the uſe of holy Communion, it will be moſt advantagious to uphold the Profeſſion of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion:</p>
               <p>For firſt, The matter thereof will be nothing elſe but the compleat and full ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of all thoſe Doctrines which are ſubſtantial unto Chriſtianity, as being neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and uſeful to advance Scripture knowledge, to hold forth the life of the Spirit, and to direct all men in the obſervation of divine Ordinances, and in the wayes of their ſeveral Vocations to walk worthy of God, which are the only things to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in our Profeſſion, if we do mind Chriſtanity for it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The form of this Engin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y be made ſuch a diſpoſition of thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, as will ſhew forth the true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of handling Scriptural Truths Poſitively, which is to infer from known and undoubted Principles, by the Evidence and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the Spirit in matters known to the conſcience, clear and undeniably concluſions, avoiding all the propoſterious wayes of School and Philoſophical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, which for the moſt part proceeding from the pride and affectation of wit and learning, be get vain janglings and humane paſſions, multiply miſtakes, and propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate impicty in the minds of thoſe that are mainly taken therewith, and addicted therunto.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, This whole Body of Divinity being made up as it ought to be, and for the end for which it is deſired, will not only be a witneſſe of the union of the Spirits of all Proteſtant Miniſters in the ſame ſaving Truth, againſt the reproach of a Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Diviſion which is ſaid to be amongſt them; but it will be a Center of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence, a ſubject of brotherly Correſpondency, and a means of mutual Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the work of the Goſpel, by which all hands will be ſtrengthened, and the hearts of thoſe that faint now by reaſon of their ſolitary walking, will be encouraged them to proceed with cheerfulneſſe, by reaſon of the conjunction of ſo great a help from all their brethren.</p>
               <p>And truly beſides the aſſiſtance and ſupport which the truth it ſelf will receive from, this Work, by being publiſhed and held forth in that wherein all the witneſſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of do agree, (which is one of the greateſt helps that can be given to it in theſe times,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:93868:27"/> of diſagreement, and therefore ſhould moſt effectually oblige our conſciences to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it) the deſign of endeavouring a concurrence by this means with our Brethren, to give them encouragement to ſtand laſt in the defence of the Cauſe, is extreamly neceſſary, and therefore alſo to our conſciences every way binding and obligatory, ſo far as we deſire them proſperity in the Cauſe?</p>
               <p>And here I mean not our brethren only that are abroad, but even thoſe that are at home alſo, whoſe ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is not yet ſet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>; and who knowes how full of Diſtraction and Deſolation it may be hereafter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God in mercy prevent it not.</p>
               <p>For if any will obſerve into how many pieces we are fallen; what the changes, breaches, and Diſſolutions are which are fallen and may fall upon us; what the effects are which this hath brought forth amongſt us, and how a liberty to all, to do without controle whatſoever every one pleaſeth, though never ſo offenſive, is ſprung up; and what the way of force (if there be a neceſſity ſtill to ſtand under it) may further bring to paſſe; If I ſay we will obſerve this, which is apparent to all, we may eaſily gather, that nothing will be more uſeful and ſerviceable to give a teſtimony of the truth unto the World, and to ſtrengthen each others hearts and hands by the unity of the Spirit in that teſtimony, then this Work will be. For in the time of our Diſſipation this may hopefully become a pillar to uphold the Truth, and therein a monument of our conjunction, an inſtrument of our concurrence in the Goſpel, and by Gods bleſſing in the End, a means to revive and reſtore the witneſſes to their heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſplendor and authority: And if there were nothing elſe but this (which is clearly our own ſpecial Intereſt) yet this alone ſhould waken up to a full Reſolution to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake this buſineſs with all ſpeed and diligence; chiefly becauſe the adverſaries make no delay to accompliſh their Deſignes againſt the wayes of Righteouſneſs, which we are bound withall our might to maintain. But beſides this neceſſity of joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſpirits to a correſponding in the Truth amongſt our ſelves againſt common adverſaries, and the unlikelihood to be able to do it any other way, or any way ſo effectually and ſo eaſily as by this means: there is another ſtrong Obligation lying upon us in reſpect of Forrain Proteſtants t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>cur with them in the ſame Cauſe.</p>
               <p>I ſaid in the beginning of the laſt parc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> this Diſcourſe that our engagement to a concurrence with Forrain Proteſtants in the common Cauſe of Religion, doth lie cloſer upon us then I finde it apprehended by many: I ſhall now endeavour to make this apparent by repreſenting two things which ought ſadly to be laid to heart, and are undenyably manifeſt in the eyes of all the world.</p>
               <p>The one is concerning Gods judgements againſt thoſe that have neglected the common Cauſe of Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>The other is concerning our own Declarations and Oathes ſtrictly obliging us to minde the ſame.</p>
               <p>For look we upon the heavy hand of God how it hath overtaken thoſe that have neglected the ſtate of Forrain Churches, we ſhall ſee that becauſe the late King and his perſecuting Prelates did not mind the true intereſt of the Proteſtant Cauſe, which is the Goſpel, becauſe they did not endeavour to help the Lord againſt the mighty, that is, to protect the Churches abroad by thoſe means which they had in their hands, and were anſwerable to the light of the truth whereof they made profeſſion, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the way of their Policy did lead them rather to fide with the common adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries for Self ends to betray the Cauſe, rather then to uphold it, therefore theſe publick Calamities have juſtly overtaken them and executed the vengeance of God upon them, that they who ſought themſelves only, without reſpect unto God and their brethren, ſhould utterly loſe themſelves without recovery, whiles God did find
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:93868:27"/> out a way to reſcue his Churches (which they deſerted) from the deſtruction which the Enemies deſigned againſt them.</p>
               <p>I alledge this concerning the late King and his violent Prelates, as to me one of the main viſible cauſes of the Judgements of God upon them, for which I conceive they have been principally caſt off; namely becauſe their betraying of the truth of the Proteſtant Cauſe was the great ſin for which Chriſt had a quarrel with them; both as Hypocrites, who pretending to ſtand for the Proteſtant Cauſe did undermine it, and deſpiſed the low condition of the Churches abroad; and as Enemies to the Goſpel, who to ſuppreſs the light thereof then breaking forth, did perſecute thoſe moſt who did moſt ſincerely profeſs and practiſe Godlineſs at home. Theſe ſins have cauſe Chriſt to fall with his iron Rod upon them to daſh them to pieces, as we have ſeen before our eyes, becauſe herein their way was Diametrically oppoſite unto his kingdom, and therefore their ſin immediatly committed againſt himſelf, whereas their others ſins and deſignes might have a more direct Relation unto the ſtate of the Nation, for which alſo the power of the Nation hath been juſtly made uſe of to overthrow them. For ſeeing in the great battel which now is a fighting between Chriſt and his Saints on the one ſide, and the Beaſt and the Kings of the Earth on the other ſide, the powers both of Heaven and Earth, that is, both of the ſpirits of men, and of the frames of States muſt be ſet a work to oppoſe each other reſpectively in their contradictory Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties: it is not poſſible that any viſible power amongſt men can remain unſhaken, And whatever is not ſubordinate unto the power which is given unto Chriſt both in Heaven and Earth, muſt be ſo ſhaken, as to be removed and aboliſhed for ever both out of Heaven and earth; hence it is that their power which they imployed not for Chriſt, but againſt him, is juſtly brought to nought, and brought to nought before all others; becauſe it did ſtrike more at the root of the Churches ſtanding, and did more deceitfully oppoſe the breaking forth of the Light of the Truth then any other Enemies whatſoever.</p>
               <p>Now they did ſtrike at the root and did more deceitfully oppoſe then others, becauſe they were entruſted with more Fundamental truth and more light then others were, and had more abilities every way to uphold the Cauſe better then others had, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Churches did rely more confidently upon them and their aſſiſtance then up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on others: but the truth and the light wherewith they were entruſted, they held in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs: and the confidence which was caſt upon them, and which they were willing to ſeem to anſwer, they betrayed utterly into the Enemies hands: chiefly then when <hi>Signor Con &amp; Banzani</hi> negotiated the Papal deſigns with them amongſt us.</p>
               <p>This I obſerve with grief for the guilt which they brought upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and not out of any perſonal hatred againſt the men: for none of them ever diſobliged me otherwiſe then in oppoſing the Proteſtant Cauſe, and by neglecting the Opportunities which I was inſtrumental to offer unto ſome of them, whereby the Goſpel might have been advanced, if they had been ſo happy as to have made uſe thereof. But they regarded not the affliction of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and therefore now they are gone captive with the firſt that are gone into captivity, <hi>Amos</hi> 6. 7. And the Juſtice of God upon them ought to be obſerved to his Glory, that others may fear, and that we our ſelves may be ware of falling under the ſame condemnation: for now the ſame duty is required of us which then was incumbent upon them, and that as ſolemnly if not more ſtrictly then ever, they were obliged them unto: for we have condemned them for that which they did neglect, and have bound our ſelves with ſolemn Remonſtrance, and a ſacred Oath to mind the common Intereſts of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants which they ſo ſinfully neglected; we then having judged them to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:93868:28"/> in the Cauſe of God, and engaged our ſelves to mend their fault, if ever God ſhould put us in a capacity ſo to do, if now when we are in that capacity, we ſhould neglect this duty, we ſhall deſerve a heavier judgement then they are fallen under, if we be found guilty of the ſame neglect.</p>
               <p>The ſolemn Remonſtrance in the name of the ſtate of the Kingdom publiſhed, <hi>Decem.</hi> 1641 before the troubles began, doth declare the whole ſtate obliged, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently every faithfull ſubject therein, according to his place, to labour by all offices of friendſhip to unite their forrain Churches with us in the ſame cauſe, &amp; to ſeek their liberty, and proſperity, as bound thereunto by charity to them, and by wiſdom for our own good, for by this means, our own ſtrength ſhall be encreaſed, and by a mutual concurrence to the ſame common End, we ſhall be able to procure the good of the whole Body of the Proteſtant Profeſſion. Here the State is engaged to mind the cauſe of the Churches abroad, and to procure the good of the whole Proteſtant Profeſſion. The cauſe of the Churches is not a meer worldly intereſt, but a ſpiritual cauſe; and the main good of the whole Proteſtant Profeſſion, is not a worldly concernment, but a Goſpel perfection by the unity of the ſpirit to build up one another in love; if this good can be procured to the whole Profeſſion, nothing will be wanting to their ſafety and proſperity: But if this good be not ſought after and endeavoured, what every elſe may be intended, will not much avail the main of their proſperity. Now to bring this to paſſe, and to unite them in a true Goſpel intereſt with us, nothing can be more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly ſubſervient then this deſign to gratifie their deſires of obtaining ſuch a Body of Practical Divinity from us. And to confirm this, and bind it ſtrongly upon our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, the ſolemn League and Covenant between God and the Nations, doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage deeply all thoſe that took that Oath, to deſire affectionately and endeavour ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, that the ſucceſs of our proceedings may be deliverance and ſafty to all Gods people, and an encouragement to other Chriſtian Churches groaning under, or in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the yoak of Antichriſtian Tyrannie, to joyn with us in the ſame or like Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation and Covenant, to the glory of God, enlargement of the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Peace and Tranquility of Chriſtian Kingdoms and Commonwealths. Theſe are deep profeſſions, as made in the preſence of God, and therefore ought to be ſo much the more conſcionably minded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>Of the Third.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>How the Work may be effected and imparted unto thoſe that have ſued for it.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO procure the compilement of this Body of Practical Divinity, the way is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready chalked out unto us, and was agreed upon by ſome of our moſt able and godly Miniſters, who before theſe Troubles, did offer themſelves unto the Work, and engaged to take their Taks to be elaborated under the direction of Doctor <hi>Uſher,</hi> the Primate of <hi>Armach,</hi> who then was in a powerful and plentiful condition, and likely to have undertaken the direction of the buſineſs. As for the way, how the matter was deſerred unto him, it may be ſeen by the adjoyned Letter, which in the year 1633. was ſent him: nor did any thing ſtop the proceeding of the Work, before our late
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:93868:28"/> troubles began in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> but the want of a compleat Plat-form, and ſome other contrivances which were referred to the <hi>Primat</hi> to effect: but ſince the troubles both here and in <hi>Ireland</hi> have unſetled all men ſo, that although there had been a Plat-form drawn up, yet few or none could have performed any thing in the Tasks which they might have taken; therefore the Work hath been hitherto in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted. But ſeeing now we are in ſome hope that the Lord will be merciful to us, and remove the cauſes of future Diſtractions, we may alſo expect that there will be faithful and able Agents found to undertake this Work, which will be ſo uſeful for all the Churches; and to bring it about, the way may be this.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Let either this, or ſome other Plat-form be held forth, that ſuch as will chuſe Tasks, may know what to pitch upon.</p>
               <p>Then let two hands be choſen as Directors, to whom all the Tasks when they ſhall be perfected may be brought in; that they may according to the Plat-form which they ſhall think fitteſt to be followed, ſet every piece in its own place, and joyn every limme of the Body to its Neighbour, till it be compleated and fitted for the Preſſe.</p>
               <p>When the Directors of the Work are choſen, let everyone who doth chooſe a Task, be obliged to notifie his Undertaking to one of them, that they may know what the Tasks are which are in hand, and by whom undertaken, that if all which is to be perfected hath not found a peculiar Workman, ſome body may be ſought out and engaged to become the Undertaker for that which ſhall be wanting; and in caſe two ſhould take the ſame Work in hand unknown to one another, the Directors may give them notice thereof, and move them to divide their Work between them, that it may be done with more expedition, or incline one of them to take ſome other Task in hand, which perhaps hath no Undertaker.</p>
               <p>An Agent alſo might be thought upon the reſiding in <hi>London,</hi> to whom from all Parts, and by whom to all Parts, the Letters ſhould be addreſſed, which muſt be written to or from the Undertakers, or to and from the Directors; and his charges ſhould be born, and by him the Tasks when they are compleated, ſhould be firſt ſent, and then conveyed unto the Directors carefully that they may not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry.</p>
               <p>The Work being effected, the way to impart it unto Forrain Churches, is no more but to get it Tranſlated into Latine, and Printed, after that it is Printed in Engliſh, which the Company of Stationers will greedily take in hand. as a Book which will yield great and ready profit: and if there ſhould be any difficulty in the printing of the Latine Copy in theſe Parts, becauſe our Stationers perhaps will not readily ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon a Book which will have no great vent here (as it it not likely the Latine Copy will have, when the Engliſh is already extant) then meanes may be uſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſome Forraine Stationer at <hi>Geneva,</hi> or elſewhere, who will not only Print it, but be induced to contract with the Tranſlators, to buy the Copy from them, becauſe the Book will ſell no leſſe abroad in Latine, then it will do at home in Engliſh; that is, exceedingly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letters">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:93868:29"/>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>The Copy of a Letter which was written by ſeveral Godly Miniſters, Undertakers in this Work of compiling a Body of Practical Divinity, to Doctor <hi>uſher</hi> the Primat of <hi>Armach</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>MOſt Reverend Father in God, <hi>Grace and Peace, with all due and dutiful Reſpects promiſed: If we ſhall ſeem bold in apprehending this opportunity of writing by this worthy Knight; yet we are confident that the important Cauſe moving us, will excuſe us, and procure not only our pardon, but alſo its approbation of your incomparable benignity and love to the Churches of Chriſt. And although it were too great inconſiderateneſs in us to imagine, that either your vigilant intelligence ſitting in that high watch Tower ſhould need our information, or your great faculty, and no leſſe facility, both of Grace and Nature, of Place and Parts to do good, and chiefly to promote the Cauſe of the Goſpel, ſhould require Arguments for incitation: yet we thought it our duty at leaſt, to ſignifie our hearty deſire for the wel-fare of Gods Church; and to prom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe that your care and zeal for it, in the courſe that we here commend, ſhall no ſooner appear, but it ſhall find us ready preſt to attend it with our beſt ſervice. It is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known unto your Grace, that the Churches of</hi> Germany <hi>are no leſſe diſtreſſed and diſtracted within the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> without, the want of inward peace moleſting them more, then of outward: Yet as the Ancient Civil</hi> Roman <hi>State, when often rent by intestine Wars, no ſooner was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded by a Forrame Power, but ſtill the breach was ſoadred up again: So the wiſer taking occaſion by theſe Wars in</hi> Germany <hi>to ſtrike while the Iron is hot, and to make a vertue of neceſſity, have hoped and ſo endeavoured to reduce the two grand diſſenting parts of theſe Churches to a wiſhed Peace and Unity, while in the fire of furious War, the two ſpiritual Swords of</hi> Luthers <hi>and</hi> Calvins <hi>Party (too keenly bent one againſt the other) being mollified, might with the more eaſie hammering be wrought into one, and ſo become the more ſtrong to fight againſt the Common Adverſary. And what do we know, whether the all-diſpoſing wiſdom of our God, hath not for this very purpoſe ſent the Sword into thoſe Parts, to launce and aſſwage the ſwellings of ſuch Apoſthumes? Now what hath been already done hercia, and by whoſe auſpicious ſetting on foot, and with what ſucceſſe and greater hopes it ſtill proceedeth (the perfection whereof we dayly pray for) we need not now to relate. That which we here preſume to propound, is a Work which either may conduce to the begetting of the Child of peace; or being brought forth to the nouriſhing of it up unto a perfect man in Chriſt. This work is the framing of a Body of Practical Divinity; for the furniſhing of thoſe Churches in ſpecial, as being moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of it, and very poor in the life and power of Religion. Now for the furtherance of ſo good and great a work, We who are Miniſters of</hi> London, <hi>whoſe names are under-written, apprehending the excellent uſe of ſuch a Work; but withall, the great difficulty of effecting in any good degree, unleſſe ſome ſuch Noble, Able, and active Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as your Grace is, give a good ſpeed unto it: are bold in the bowels of Chriſt, and in a Brotherly compaſſion of the ſame myſtical Body, to implore your Piety and wiſdom, not only in giving Counſel and Direction, but aſſiſtance alſo by your worthy Example, joyning Head, Heart, and Hand together, for the advancement and accompliſhment of ſo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and deſireable a Work: And the rather are we emboldned to deſire the engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your Grace herein, ſith we are Credibly informed, that your Grace formerly hath</hi>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:93868:29"/> 
                     <hi>much deſired ſuch a Work to be undertaken and effected. And who can better deſcribe a Methode, manner, matter, and meanes for this then your ſelf, whom the Lord hath ſo richly furniſhed with ſo excellent gifts of Wiſdom, Learning, Charity and Zeal, for the perfecting of the Saints, for the Miniſtry, for the Edifying of the Body of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thus recommending all this to your Chriſtian Care and Piety, with our humbleſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices and dayly prayers for the increaſe of Gods Grace and bleſſing upon your vigilancy in keeping the ſtock of God from Ravenous wolves, and advancing the Goſpel in the power and purity of it, as well abroad as at home, we humbly take our leave, attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what ſervice your Grace will Command us, when once your piety and Prudence hath ſet us down an Ample and full Platform of the whole Body of Divinity, ſo as we may be able to diſcern all the limbs and lineaments of it; and ſo taking a full view of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Model, each may make Choice of that piece in ſpecial which he findes himſelf fitteſt to frame and poliſh, untill by this means the whole Building ſhall be happily and the more eaſily finiſhed, many hands making light work.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Graces moſt humble Servants in the Lord,
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Gouge</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Stoughton</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Downam</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Henry Burton</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Geo. Walker</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Nicolas Morton</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Sidr. Simpſon</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Adoniram Byfield</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Rich Culverwell</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Obadiah Sedgwick</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Geo. Hughes</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Joſeph Symonds.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>For his loving Friend <hi>M. John Dury, Theſe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MR.</hi> Dury, <hi>I am glad that you are ſtill willing to take ſome pains about the procuring of a Body of Practical Divinity; a Work which I have long wiſhed for; and which formerly my heart was in, and my hand would have been in, if God had been pleaſed to continue our Peace: for when you brought over the Letters from the Forrain Churches, wherein they made it their Requeſt unto us to gratifie their Churches with ſome En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors about the compilement of this Work: which were ſeconded by a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the Miniſters in and about London unto me, when I was in Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land many years ago, I was very glad of the Motion, and laid it very ſeriouſly to heart, and conferred with ſome of my Brethren about it, that we might bring the Work to ſome perfection. Doctor</hi> Downam <hi>the then Biſhop of</hi> London-Derry, <hi>was a man whoſe ſtudies were much bent</hi>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:93868:30"/> 
                     <hi>that way: for which cauſe it was referred to him; and he readily did under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the Task to draw up a Model or Plat-form, according to which that Syſteme or Body might be compiled, that the Miniſters who had written to me might be able to chooſe their Tasks, and ſet themſelves awork about it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Model he promiſed to ſend unto me to reviſe it before it ſhould be imparted to the foreſaid Miniſters, that in our joint name it might be ſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. But he either for want of health, or ſome other impediments, did not expedite the work before his death, and when the Troubles of</hi> Scotland <hi>did begin: which by reaſon of my Lord of</hi> Straffords <hi>intermedling had ſome Reflexion upon us in</hi> Ireland; <hi>and not long after I being come over hither, he the Biſhop of</hi> Derry <hi>being dead, the Troubles of</hi> Ireland <hi>taking fire, at the proceedings of the then Parliament here, and the great diſtractions of this and the two Nations increaſing ever ſince, I could not do what was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired of me, and what I heartily deſired might have been done, and wiſh yet may be done; for it will never be too late or unſeaſonable to ſet upon ſuch an Enterpriſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If therefore by your Solicitation and pains you can oblige thoſe that in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, or in and about this City are able and willing to undertake it, I think you will do a work very acceptable to all that are Godly, and profitable to all the Churches at home and abroad. Let me therefore intreat you to proceed, that whiles there is any appearance of doing good to our Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, we may not neglect the Opportunity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As for the Model of the Heads which you have ſhewed unto me;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt, I ſhall adviſe this, that the Precognitions may not be inſiſted upon largely, but as briefly and ſubſtantially as may be; and if ſome References be made unto ſuch Authors as handle the Heads of the Precognitions more at large, it may give ſatisfaction to ſuch as will be more curious and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to ſee things amply handled.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly, my advice is, that the work may be contracted to as few hands as may be; who may meet and confer together about it when they are perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Tasks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly, I would not have the Work too large and Voluminous for ſeveral Reaſons, yet as full of matter as it can be: and where Enlargement may be thought uſeful, References may be made to ſuch Author, as uſe them moſt effectually.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Laſtly, Concerning the Caſes of Conſcience which ſhould be handled in this Body, I think they may be brought in and inſerted under every Head of matter whereunto they belong.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This is for the preſent that which I would ſuggest. I pray God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:93868:30"/> 
                     <hi>direct and aſſiſt you and all thoſe that go about it; And what I ſhall be able to do towards the incouragement of able Workmen therein, you may be confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſhall not be wanting from</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your loving friend Ja. Armachanus.</signed>
                     <dateline>From my ſtudy, <date>
                           <hi>Decemb.</hi> 14. 1653.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>A Letter written divers years ago by the Author of the foregoing Treatiſe to M. <hi>Samuel Hartlib,</hi> concerning the difference of Practical and Caſe Divinity.</head>
                  <p>TO ſpeak of the difficulty you propoſe concerning Caſe and Practical Divinity, I do thus conceive of the matter, that if men would not be ſlack to do what they ought, the difficulties would reſolve themſelves in the action; yet to ſatisfie the Scruple, and anſwer the deſire you have, I ſay thus, That in all Actions Two things are to be conſidered. Firſt, that which is Eſſential to it. Secondly, that which is Circumſtantial.</p>
                  <p>The Eſſential parts of all Actions are two: The proper End for which it ought to be taken in hand, and the means of attaining that End, which is the Formal way of proceeding in going about that which is intended to be done.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Two, <hi>viz.</hi> the End and the Means are in all Actions certain and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate; But the Circumſtantial part of the actions is infinite, according to the variety of Accidental Circumſtances.</p>
                  <p>Now from this diviſion of the parts of all actions, which is ſo plain and natural that nothing can ſeem to me more facile, diſtinct and orderly, we may gather what is to be done in this matter, and what the Methode both of Practical and Caſe Divinity ought to be as well in themſelves, as the one toward the other. For Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Divinity containeth properly the determination of the Ends of all our actions, to ſhew how they are ſubordinate to Godlineſs and the Rules whereby the actions are to be directed to their own proper ends.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Two things ſo far as they are expreſly ſet down in the Scriptures, ought to be explained in that which we may call the Body of Practical Divinity (for in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing there is no proper diſtinction between Practical and caſe Divinity) according to the general Idea which I once conceived and ſent to you; <hi>viz.</hi> that the Firſt part of Practical Divinity be concerning the Eſſentials of a Chriſtian ſtate; the Second concerning the Accidentals as he is a Chriſtian in this or that Calling. We ſee this is the ordinary Method of the Apoſtles in all their Epiſtles: therefore the Practical Directions, ſhould, as in every particular, ſo in the whole ſtate of a mans life be divided and ordered, that whatſoever is plainly in the Scriptures determined, concerning either the Eſſential Ends or Means of Chriſtianity, or concerning the Accidental Ends and Means of Chriſtianity in a certain Calling, that ſhould be
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:93868:31"/> fully explained from the Texts wherein it is delivered, which ſhould be according to the order of the matters contained in them <hi>(viz.</hi> as they are nearer or further ſubordinate to the main End of Gods glory and our own Salvation) ſet down in their ſeveral Ranks, whereof as ſoon as ever I can, I will labour to give you a more full and demonſtrative Draught then that which I have heretofore; ſo the whole Body of plain Rules and undoubted Truth, ſufficiently explained in the Ends and Means of all Eſſential &amp; Accidential parts of a Chriſtian life is to be the matter of that which is properly in a ſtrict ſenſe called here Practical Divinity: and then all the Circumſtantials and determinate Accidents which the Scripture hath left to every mans conſcience to work upon in the ſeveral Occurrences of his life; wherein the variety of his Circumſtances, changes the nature of the action, and makes a man doubtful what to do, or not to do, is to be the matter of that which you call Caſe-Divinity.</p>
                  <p>Now who doth not ſee that theſe two muſt be joyned together either in one body of Treatiſe, or elſe ſo, if they be two ſeveral Volumes and Treatiſes, yet in the Method they may be all one, ſo that the caſes muſt be referred every one to his Action of which he is a Caſe; juſt as in Grammer the Exceptions muſt needs be referred to the Rules and every Exception to his own Rule: otherwiſe all is in a confuſion; ſo it is here<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the caſes are as it were Exceptions of the General Rule, which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt needs be firſt delivered; from whence you ſee that I am not of your minde when you ſay that Caſe-Divinity muſt firſt be ruled before Practical Divinity; for Caſe Divinity cannot be Ruled except you have firſt a Rule to Rule it by. Now the Rule is that which I ſay is the matter of Practical Divinity; <hi>viz.</hi> all ſuch expreſſe Determinations as the Scripture doth deliver concerning all the parts and actions, either of the general and ſubſtantial, or of the particular and accidental ſtate of Chriſtianity.</p>
                  <p>When theſe expreſſe determinations are ſet down in their natural order, then we have a Rule of underſtanding and conſcience by which every man is able to direct himſelf afterwards in the ſeveral Occurrences as his occaſions may fall out; for the ſpirit of Obedience dwelling in his conſcience, and being informed and ſtrengthened by the Rule of the Word, will diſcern the duty which is moſt requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to be performed in the particular occaſion wherein a man is; Neither is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible as I ſuppoſe, that all the incident caſes of this nature can be truly determined, ſo that they will ſatisfie every mans conſcience. For the different meaſures of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and of the apprehenſions of the Rule, make the conſcience doubtful; And therefore except the ſetled and infallible Rules be firſt received and propoſed, all particular deciſions of doubtful caſes will become nothing elſe but a matter of inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricable diſpute, by which means inſtead of a Body of Practical Truths, we ſhall have a new kind of Polemical Divinity in matters of Practice, becauſe the prepoſterous courſe being taken to begin at doubts, before the true Rules be known whereby to frame our life, we ſhall hardly ever finde the right way. For after that different opinions are once taken up in matters of doubt, we ſee how hardly they are laid down; and how that men before they will ſeem to have erred in the particular deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the doubt, will ſometimes ſtrain the ſenſe of many Principles, as in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Theory the Papiſts do plainly.</p>
                  <p>Therefore I think that to begin at caſes is a prepoſterous courſe every way, and to do as you ſay that theſe caſes ſhould firſt be ſent into all Churches to be allowed of and then publiſhed; I think is dangerous to cauſe much contradiction, and a great deal more laborious then to make up the chief and more profitable part of the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:93868:31"/> Work: which if it be well done, may ſtand by it ſelf without contradiction or fear of oppoſition, being clearly the truth both in the Word and in every mans Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: And then either when this is done, or whiles it is a doing, if ſome be ſet a work to gather Caſes as you ſay out of all M. S. Letters, conferences, correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, &amp;c. he ought to referre the Caſes to the Heads of the Practical part, ſo that all the Caſes ſtand in the ſame order wherein the Infallible Rules of Practical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections were delivered correſponding in the ſame matters, as more particularly and as it were Individual Determinations of the ſame End and Means of an Action, or rather as an application of the Rule delivered to a particular object wherein every body might not hit the right way of proceeding.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="letter">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:93868:32"/>
                  <head>An Extract of a Letter, written by <hi>George Horne</hi> Doctor in Divinity, and publick Profeſſor of Hiſtory in the Univerſity of Leyden;</head>
                  <head>To <hi>Samuel Hartlib.</hi> Eſq;</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IDea illa Theologiae Practica Domini Duraei, it a me affecit, ut vix quicquam a Te hactenùs profectum magis. Crede mihi, nullum Divinius remedium ſedandis illis Polemicis inter Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes affectibus rixoſis, &amp; verae pietati propagandae etiam apud Atheos &amp; Haereticos convenientius. Nunquam illud ingens Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicum Opus ad optatum &amp; ſtabilem finem deducetur, niſi hoc effecto. Incredibiliter mihi tota Diſpoſitio &amp; Scopus placent: Et quid quaeſo remorae, quo minùs Veſter Ille Ioſua, Suâ Authoritate id intra breve tempus Orbi exhibere poſsit? Abundat Britannia Viris capaciſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, &amp; ad hunc laborem natis. Longè profectò ſatiùs in ejuſmodl Opere occupari curas &amp; manus plurium quàm in conſarcinandis Commentariis Scripturarum, quibus jam obrutus eſt Orbis &amp; Eccleſiae velut ſub onere quodam gemunt. Legam autem &amp; relegam totum Opus attentiùs, &amp; ſi quid incidat, quod aliquid ad Templi illius Hieroſolymitani ſtructuram conferre poſsit, ſtudioſè annotabo; quanquam profectò eâ in parte Veſtrates palmam obtinent, ut id Opus non aliundè quàm ab Anglia exſpectare Chriſtianus Orbis poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit. Contulerunt tot pientiſsimae Animae, tot jam annis copioſam materiam; quid reſtat, niſi ut Salomo aliquis, evocatis Artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, Templum longè illo Ceremoniali magnificentius, exſtruat?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:93868:32"/>
                  <head>In Engliſh.</head>
                  <p>MR. <hi>Dury</hi> his Idea of Practical Divinity, hath pleaſed me as much as any thing that ever you ſent me. Believe me, there is not a more Soveraigne remedy then this, for the Putting an end to the controverſies and quarrels now between Proteſtants; nor fitter for the Propagating of true piety, even amongſt Atheiſts and Hereticks: That great Work of Pacification, will never be brought to the deſired end of ſettlement, but by this means. The whole Order and Scope of this Work do pleaſe me exceedingly. And (I pray you) what can hinder, Your <hi>Joſua</hi> from impoſing it on the World by his Authority within a ſhort time? England doth abound with men, that are moſt fit for this Work, and as it were born to perform it. It were certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly much better, to have the cares and hands of many men imployed about ſuch a Work, as this, then in compiling of Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries on Scripture, wherewith the world is already over whelmed, and the Churches groan under them as under a burden. But I will read over this whole Tract more heed fully, and if any thing come into my mind, which may conduce towards the building of this Temple of Jeruſalem, I will carefully ſet it down. Although in this part, your Engliſh men do ſo excell, that the Chriſtian World needs not to have it done by any elſe; So many godly Souls having for theſe many years been preparing abundant matter for it; What is now to be done, but for ſome <hi>Solomon</hi> to call his Workmen together, and build up a Temple, far more magnificent, then the Ceremoniall one was?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="essay">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:93868:33"/>
               <head>The Expedient for a Correſpondencie with Forrain Proteſtants.</head>
               <p>THe complaint which the Prophet David made in his low condition, may now be taken up in our dayes by all that favour the duſt of Sion, and take pleaſure in her ſtones; namely <hi>that her bones are ſcattered at the graves mouth, as one cleaveth wood upon the ground,</hi> Pſal. 141. 7. for if we look upon the Churches which make Profeſſion of the ſame ſaving truth in oppoſition to Popery as now they are divided and broken; we ſhall ſee them almoſt, if not altogether, as uſeleſſe one to another as dry bones, ſcattered up and down, ready to be caſt into the grave, or as chippes of wood lying on the ground onely fit to be gathered and burnt; therefore our reſolution ſhould be the ſame which the Prophet took in the words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing upon his complaint. <hi>But our eyes are to thee O God the Lord; in thee is our truſt leave not our ſouls destitute.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is none other that can help but he in ſuch a caſe Let then our eyes be turned onely towards him; becauſe our expectation will not be in vain, if we flie to him for refuge; for we have a word of promiſe giving us aſſurance that he will help; for <hi>Moſes</hi> hath ſaid. <hi>That the Lord ſhall judge his people and repent him for his ſervants, when he ſeeth that their power is gone, and there is none</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut. 32. 36.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſhut up or left:</hi> and the Prophet Iſaiah hath declared for our comfort, that <hi>when the enemie ſhall come in like a flood, the Spirit of the Lord ſhall lift up a ſtandard against him.</hi> It is evident then, that we have a <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai. 59. 19.</hi>
                  </note> ground to hope that the Lord in his own time will make our dry bones to ſtir, and live and joyn together, and being clothed with fleſh and skin to ſtand upon their feet and become a great and mighty army: for there is no condition of the Saints ſo weak and low, but God can; and when it is fit, will alſo raiſe them out of it: becauſe he hath in a readineſs means which he hath appointed to that effect; and when his ſpirit will breath upon them, to ſet them a work; the buſineſs will be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed.</p>
               <p>Now the means by which the Lord doth execute his wonderful counſel, and by which he will bring to paſſe his excellent work; is two fold; the one is the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the Truth, by the armour of light; and the ſword of the Spirit, which is the word of God, to diſcover the hidden things of darkneſs, and ſweeping away the refuge of lies and Hypocriſie to ſtay the wicked one and conſume the man of ſin; which part of his work is already well advanced in the midſt of all theſe diſtractions, and diviſions of parties: and the other is by the unitie of the Spirit, in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints, to bring the whole Body ſo to depend upon the head Jeſus Chriſt; that it ſhall appear at laſt ſitly joyned together and compacted by that which every joint ſupplyeth, according to the effectual working in the meaſure of every part to make the encreaſe of the Body to the edifying of it ſelf in love: and this part of the work although it is very little advanced in appearance, yet there are Preparatives towards it, which are not inconſiderable, if rightly weighed and taken notice of: and whereof in due time a more full account may be given: but for the preſent we
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:93868:33"/> ſhall onely ſhew ſome motives for which we ſhould attend unto this part of Gods Counſell, and ſuggeſt a way by which we may help forward the effect thereof, and become inſtrumental towards others in furthering his work.</p>
               <p>The Motives which ſhould induce us to mind the deſign which God hath of unit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Saints together are ſo many in the Holy Scriptures, and ſo clearly ſet forth, that a Volum might be written thereof if we would be large: but it ſhall ſuffice at preſent only, to point at the places where the Holy Ghoſt doth urge the duty upon us: if we look upon 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. The ſcope of the Apoſtle is there to demonſtrate that all ſpiritual gifts are beſtowed upon the Church Militant on earth, to the end that they may be made uſe of to profit withall by the ſeveral members of the myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Body in the unitie thereof: and in chap. 13. the grace of Charitie is ſaid to be ſo neceſſary for this effect; that without it none other grace is profitable, either to our ſelves or towards others; in the fourth of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſ. ver.</hi> 1. till 17. the Apoſtle ſheweth that no man doth walk worthy of the Vocation wherewith he is called to the Profeſſion of the Goſpel, who doth not intend and endeavour by humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, meekneſs, long ſuffering and forbearance of others in love to keep the Unitie of the Spirit in the bond of Peace; and whatſoever throughout the Scripture is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded concerning love (which is the great and new Commandment) and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in the 1 Epiſtle of <hi>John,</hi> it tendes all to oblige our conſcience to this main duty of ſeeking the Unitie of the Spirit amongſt Saints, and of keeping it in the bond of Peace: and if the Apoſtles words, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 1, 2. be laid to heart, they will convince any man that hath any feeling of his duty in this matter, If, ſaith he, there be any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of Love, if any fellowſhip of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, if any bowels and mercies; fulfill ye my joy, that ye be like minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord, of one mind, &amp;c. intimating that without the care of this duty; all the joy and happineſs which Saints ought to further in one another, is quite loſt and utterly made void; which in theſe our dayes we find experimentally to be too true, by reaſon of our diviſions and ſtrivings, for which the name of God is blaſphemed amongſt the adverſaries, and the Profeſſion of the truth amongſt our ſelves is diſhonoured.</p>
               <p>Now to remedy this great evil, and to remove the ſcandals ariſing from thence, for which a woe is denounced and in ſome meaſure executed againſt us, the eaſie way which is ſuggeſted is, to ſet a foot a Religious Correſpondencie with Forrain Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants to carry on a Goſpel intereſt amongſt Chriſtians, not by ſtrength or might, but in a Goſpel way, by a friendly Correſpondencie and concurrence in Counſels; to hold forth unanimouſly, the matters of Faith and Doctrine wherein we all fully agree, and do own the ſame ſaving truths; and to ſet a foot the Practice of the ſame Rules of duties by walking therein, to oppoſe ignorance and profanneſs, to baniſh confuſion and diſorderlineſs in worſhip, and be no more ſtrangers to one anothers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, but to entertain a mutual Care for each others good and the progreſs of the Goſpel in the world, to which effect a ſetled correſpondencie upon Religious grounds and Principles; between us and our neighbour Proteſtants, will be both an eaſie and in Gods way a powerfull means; which Correſpondencie may be thus contrived and brought about, We forthwith intend a ſyſteme or body of Divinity, wherein all the Engliſh writings of Practical Divinity and Caſes of Conſcience ſhall be digeſted in Engliſh and Latine, and we intend the intertainment of ſtrangers in a Colledge here, from whence our Learning may be carried forth in moſt Languages by ſuch Students, and all good works advanced by the ſame hands, to which we already find great forwardneſs in this Nation, not only to labour in the work, but alſo to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:93868:34"/> contribute in matter of charge; And of this Work in inſtituting a Colledge <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagandis bonis operibus</hi> we ſhall give Advertiſment to our friends as occaſion preſents; not doubting but ſince the Lord hath given us in England ſuch a meaſure of light and Peace, but there will appear a ready heart amongſt our Nations for the rowling away the reproach upon us, of having much of faith, and little of Works; and from this Colledge and Truſtees about this Work, we ſhall be ready to maintain ſuch Correſpondence with our Brethren beyond the Seas, that they and we may have cauſe to rejoyce, and our enemies to mourn, and this charge of Correſpondency fixed upon the Truſtees for the Work above ſaid.</p>
               <p>The incouragement of this Correſpondency intended, riſeth much from the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable bleſſing hath accompanied the Letter and Epiſtle of the Saints, witneſſe thoſe in the New Teſtament, what <hi>Luther, Calvin,</hi> and others have done that way, and what dayly ſucceſs therein of Epiſtoling, there are clouds of witneſſes.</p>
               <p>For the preſent we judge it meet, that what any Forrain Divine hath now to Communicate, might come either to the Vice-Chancelour of the Univerſity, or the Miniſters ſitting at White-hall weekly for approbation of Miniſters. And theſe things we deſire may be remembred at home and abroad in the prayers of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that we may not make forfeiture of our mercies by our ſloth and negligence, and ſit down by the ſtarving ſluggard with <hi>non putarem.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>IN the names ſubſcribed to the Latin Letter, read <hi>Hopſius.</hi> item <hi>P. T. paſtor Schreſheimi.</hi> item. <hi>Belsteinenſis</hi> &amp; <hi>Beilſteinenſi.</hi> In the ſubſcription to the Engliſh Letter read <hi>Hopſius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Schreſheim</hi> &amp; <hi>Orzen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN the quotations of Scripture places, pag. 1. read in Margin. 1 <hi>Peter.</hi> pag. 2. in Margin read. <hi>John</hi> 13. ibid. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 22. pag. 4. lin. 39. read 17. 3. pag. 17. lin. 36. read <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 47. p. 21. l. 35. r. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 20. p. 37. l. 11. r. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 59. p. 41. l. 37. r. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 7.</p>
            <p>In the words of the diſcourſe pag. 3. lin. 17. read <hi>manifeſt my ſelf.</hi> pag. 5. lin. 35. read <hi>Precognitions</hi> pag. 6. lin. 31. read <hi>main heads.</hi> ibid. lin. ult. read. <hi>thoſe</hi> pag. 34. lin. 21. read <hi>Diſputations</hi> pag. 36. lin. 26. read <hi>pertaining</hi> pag. 37. lin. 15. read <hi>from my judgement.</hi> pag. 42. lin. 4 read <hi>to one end.</hi> ibid. lin. 15. read <hi>rectifie</hi> pag. 44. lin. 35. read <hi>Panrani.</hi> pag. 45. lin. 8. read <hi>the forrain</hi> p. 46. l. 26. read <hi>upon, reſiding.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
